<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An additional supplement to the Eirenikon, or, Peaceable considerations of Christs peaceful kingdome to come upon the earth in the thousand years Rev. 20, lately published, 1665.</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34218</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14147854</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14147854</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102104</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102104)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An additional supplement to the Eirenikon, or, Peaceable considerations of Christs peaceful kingdome to come upon the earth in the thousand years Rev. 20, lately published, 1665.</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 2-68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Sherwin.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Resurrection.</term>
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:102104:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102104:1"/>
            <head>An Additional Supplement to the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, OR, Peaceable Conſiderations of Chriſts peaceful Kingdome to come upon the Earth in the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. lately publiſhed, 1665.</head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The PREFACE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Chriſtian Brethren,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Having in my late <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, pag. 2. declared my purpoſe, to make ſome parallels of part of the Propheſie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> with the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the book of <hi>Revelations</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which is plainly a Divine Myſtical Comment upon the particulars of the 4th and 5th Monarchies contained in <hi>Daniels</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: that is, of what was more fully to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed under the <hi>Roman</hi> and Chriſts Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, both before the Stone cut out of the Mountain without hands had ſo ſtrucken the Image on the feet and toes thereof, that it was wholly deſtroyed; and alſo afterwards, when the Stone was become a Mountain, and filled the whole earth: But by the hand of God upon me then, ſhewing me my miſtake in reſpect of the manner of Chriſts coming, and of Chriſts Kingdome, that it was not Myſtical (but perſonal) as before I apprehended, until I found that coming was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the day of Judgment; and likewiſe upon occaſion of thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parallels of the three <hi>Babels,</hi> which I at firſt thought not of, until by Gods guidance led unto them; I was ſo far thereby taken off from my former purpoſe, That onely in the 5th Chapter concerning thoſe three <hi>Babels,</hi> I did but briefly touch upon that intended parallel of the Books of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelations.</hi> But ſince (through Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful goodneſs) having further diſcovery of the uſefulneſs of ſuch an endeavour, I have accordingly (by his grace) ſet upon that buſineſs in this enſuing order.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:2"/>
               <p>Firſt, to ſet down a brief and plain Abridgment of the ſum of the Prophetical Viſions in <hi>Daniel</hi> contained: Firſt in <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> dream of the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mage, Chap. 2, and <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſion of the ſame matter, namely, of four Earthly Monarchies under four Beaſts, to paſs before Chriſts glorious Kingdom, take place, Chap. 7. wherein is ſhewed to <hi>Daniel</hi> a Jew, the beginning of the Judgment at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the fourth Beaſt, which was not ſhewed to <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> a Gentile (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> obſerve,) though he ſaw the Kingdome of the Stone. A Second Prophetical Viſion was given unto <hi>Dan.</hi> c. 8. of the ſubduing of the ſecond Monarchy, [for the ruine f the firſt, to wit, of <hi>Babylon,</hi> had been ſhewed before to <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 7.4.] namely, of the Kingdome of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, the founder of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Monarchy, with the dividing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to his four Captains, jointly ſucceeding him towards the four winds (as the Text ſpeaketh) where the Spirit of God paſſing by the <hi>Greek</hi> affairs for a long time, unto that one King of fierce countenance, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus Epiphanes,</hi> at laſt riſing out of one of them, whoſe wicked act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt the Church of the Jews, is ſhewed ſhould be ſhort, and his death terrible towards the end of that 8. chap.</p>
               <p>In chap. 9. <hi>Daniel</hi> had a third Viſion of the 70 weeks of years, till Chriſt had finiſhed his work of Redemption, and confirmed the Covenant with many, both Jews and Gentiles, for that time.</p>
               <p>But his fourth and laſt Viſion, chap. 10.11.12. ſets forth before him again the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Greek,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdoms, with the beginning of Chriſts Monarchy; yet chiefly in the 11 chap. he ſpeaks of the inteſtine wars, and thereby the decaying of the Kingdome of <hi>Grecia</hi> under two principal heads of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> called the Kings of the South and North, mutually battering down each other, and yet both of them ſadly oppreſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he poor Jews that lay between them, from <hi>v.</hi> 4, to 21. and from thence to 36. is ſet down a more full diſcription of that vile and wicked <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> before the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom took place, who at laſt was ſaid to come out of one of the four heads, chap. 8.9. being that wicked little horn, [that probably may well be reckoned as a type of the great Antichriſt] in whoſe ruine the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> Kingdome, and <hi>Javans</hi> rage together ended.</p>
               <p>Now after the brief conſideration of theſe Viſions, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in ſuch a ſaid Parallel, reſpecting the 4th and 5th Monarchy in <hi>Daniel,</hi> according as our bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Saviour by his divine wiſdom hath been pleaſed to open and ſet them down for the uſe of his Chriſtian Church in his very uſeful book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> for theſe laſt times, and leaving particular obſervations and applications to Chriſtians in their
<pb facs="tcp:102104:2"/>private Meditations, aiming herein at brevity and clearneſs, I ſhall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my ſelf onely</p>
               <p>Thirdly, To ſet down ſomewhat in general to thoſe purpoſes (if God will) in the laſt place. N w in conſidering of theſe, I have to the ſaid purpoſes or brevity and clearneſs, profeſtedly avoided all thoſe perplexing controverſies whereby ſome have unhappily obſcured both the ſcope and meaning of the Viſions, as likewiſe, ſome commonly miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken expreſſions, as, That the Thrones were caſt down,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onec throni e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ati ſunt as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nus, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Sept</hi>
                  </note> for the Thrones were ſet, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.9. having en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eavoured (as God hath enabled me) to ſeek out the moſt genuine ſenſe, and the moſt clear and evident drift of theſe Viſions in the main of them, with divers natural explications from the matter and ſubject of them (which by the aſſiſtance of Gods spirit, (together with the Rule of his Word) I either have, or ſhall obſerve to be moſt conſonant unto truth.</p>
               <p>Yet in the intended Parallel between the Fourth, or <hi>Roman,</hi> and Chriſts Kingdom held out in <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ye may with me take notice of what Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſets down of their different handling thereof, namely, that it is done in <hi>Daniel</hi> more darkly, <hi>ſummatim &amp; in genere,</hi> ſummarily, and in general onely; but in the <hi>Revelation, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulatim &amp; in ſpecie,</hi> more particularly and ſpecially: Or, ſaith he in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Roman</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpire <hi>in imaginè confuſa:</hi> But Chriſts Revelation contains the <hi>ſeries rerum gerendarum,</hi> the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of things to be done, according to the diverſe fates and ſtates of the Church; in which reſpect many things in <hi>Daniel</hi> were ſaid to be ſealed up, and ſhut up till the time of the end, as Ch. 12.9. till Chriſt Jeſus the true and faithful Witneſs, had ſo Divinely made them known for his Churches great advantage by his Servant <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This further (beloved Brethren) I would advertiſe you of, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Viſions, we ſhall (beyond former intentions) endeavour to repreſent ſomewhat of <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Viſions, and eſpecially from Chap. 37. to the end of that Book; who b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing a Prophet of the ſame time of the Captivity, though not in the ſame place with <hi>Daniel,</hi> yet by the ſame Spirit was guided into the ſame truth, then made known to Gods people for their comfort, yet one explaining the other in ſome things.</p>
               <p>Therefore after <hi>Ezekiel</hi> (chap. 37.) had the Viſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> laſt and great Reſtauration, when both they and the reſt of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould be united into one ſtick; that it might not be doubted how it ſhould be done, chap. 38, 39. he ſhewed how the <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi> of the preceding times (then) namely, the Pope and the Turk, ſhould be deſtroyed; and that the happy conſequents of this might be known (then) to the faithful <hi>Jews,</hi> he hath another Viſion of the <hi>New-Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102104:3"/>ſuited much unto the Jewiſh ſtate, but very excellent, and in this eſpecially, that the Name thereof ſhould be <hi>[Jehovah Shamma]</hi> the Lord is there, chap. 40. to the end of the Book, which our Saviour in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, more ſuitable to the Chriſtian Churches excellency, ſets forth, as coming out of Heaven from God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. which he ſhewed to Saint <hi>John,</hi> was to ſucceed upon the deſtruction of Antichriſt and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices in the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, chap. 19.11. to the end, when ſo great joy had been, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, for that Brides making ready of Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, ſo largely celebrated in the beginning of that Chapter. The like I may briefly hint of Chriſts Spouſe, in that Song of Songs which (as Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> judiciouſly obſerves) all along to be Prophetical to the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Jews, with the Gentiles more abundant coming in at their riſing, (as the Prophets phraſe is) <hi>Eſ.</hi> 60.3, 4, 5, 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and whoſe fulneſs ſhall be the greateſt riches of the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12. which Spouſe will then in the New-Jeruſalem, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. be the Lambs Wife, in that holy City where ſhe and Chriſt will be made perfect in one, and one member with another, who ſince the Apoſtles, believed through their Word, till all theſe ſhould ſo be perfect, (as our Saviour prayed) <hi>John</hi> 17.20, 21, 23. that then in the time of the New-Jeruſalem, the whole world might both believe and know that God had ſent him into the world, when his glory in his Kingdom on Earth ſhould be ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſet up there; which Kingdom at his death he willed to them (as a Legacy) or birth-right, with his Fathers Conſent and Grant (the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles being Witneſſes thereto) as <hi>v.</hi> 24. of the ſame Chapter, that they might all have their part with him there, and that (as our bleſſed Saviour further teacheth) for a thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. to which purpoſe tends likewiſe the 45 <hi>Pſalm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having briefly given you an Account of this my poor endeavour for the benefit of faithful Chriſtians, and for the greater evidence and clearneſs of theſe (amongſt many) ſo little believed myſteries of ſuch Chriſts coming to begin the Judgment, and ſuch manner of his raiſing up the Saints in the time of his ſaid viſible glorious Kingdom on Earth in the thouſand years: I ſhall endeavour by the further aſſiſtance of his Grace and Spirit, and by the evidence of his Sacred Word of Truth, and in the further explication whereof, Chriſt Jeſus himſelf hath (above what was afforded <hi>Daniel</hi> in this Book) as the true and faithful witneſs ſo unſealed and opened to his Church in that Divine Book which was ſo gloriouſly given unto him in that Viſion which St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things to come; and hereupon in reference to ſuch a future Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, we have premiſed this enſuing ſhort Abridgment of the whole, that the particular branches thereof might the better be made uſe of to
<pb facs="tcp:102104:3"/>their ſeveral due intendments, by ſuch as are rightly converſant in them; and the greater light of truth might ſo be made evident to all ſerious and impartial ſeekers thereof, by the bleſſing of God thereupon, as God may order their Meditations for their own and others edifying.</p>
               <p>Now as that ſhort compriſal in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> on the fifth Chapter of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> pag. 27. as likewiſe in the Letter <hi>May</hi> 20. 1664. in the <hi>Fore-runner,</hi> are (as it were) an <hi>A. B. C.</hi> for ſome Chriſtians to learn to ſpell out the meaning of the ſubſtance of things contained in that Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> which were to come. So may the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſhort Abridgment of the Viſions of <hi>Daniel</hi> be for this Book, when they come to be a little acquainted with it; and by the help of both which together, I hope by Gods bleſſing both great clearneſs of the truth, and of the neceſſity of the ſubſtance of the Doctrine of Chriſts Kingdom upon earth, may unto many ſorts of men in due time be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably made evident, to be ſuch Divine Truth as is both profitable and neceſſary, appearing ſo infallibly and ſtrongly grounded upon both thoſe Divine and bleſſed Books of holy Scripture, which being once rightly underſtood, will manifeſt them to be (as indeed they are) the ſure key for the right opening of many other Prophetical Scriptures in the Old Teſtament, and ſundry other pertinent Texts in the New, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are little rightly underſtood by moſt ſorts of men.</p>
               <p>But after all ſuch outward means to bouſed, with humble and faithful prayer, meditation and conference of them, muſt then be likewiſe inwardly done by him who is ſaid to open the underſtanding of his Diſciples together, after his reſurrection, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.35. to make them underſtand the Scriptures: To whoſe moſt gracious guidance and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I commend both you, and all truly Chriſtian and teachable Spirits, ſeeking for a bleſſing to you, and all ſuch in my prayers upon this my poor and weak endeavours, with all other good means to any like purpoſe. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1665.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Therein remaining yours, and their faithful Servant in him our great Lord, in what I may be uſeful. <hi>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="comparisons">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102104:4"/>
               <head>An Endeavour of a ſhort and plain A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of the Prophetical Viſions in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> Propheſie, in reference to a Parallel of what is foretold of the 4th or <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, and of Chriſts Kingdome on earth, further explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt in the book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> for the uſe of the Chriſtian Church.</head>
               <p>IN the ſecond Chapter,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nebuchadn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>z<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> dreamex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</note> 
                  <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> a Gentile (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) had in a dream repreſented unto him a great Image, ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing forth t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e four worldly Monarchies; the firſt of which was his own <hi>Caldean</hi> Kingdom, whereof he was the head of gold, to contirue after him in <hi>Evilmerodack</hi> his Son, and <hi>Beiſhazzar</hi> his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child, unto which was then to ſucceed the breaſt and arms of ſilver, beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n by <hi>Darius,</hi> and ſoon after by <hi>Cyrus</hi> in the Monarchy of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians;</hi> to which ſucceeded the third of braſs, as <hi>Daniel</hi> expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, namely, the <hi>Grecian</hi> Impire, begun in <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great; and the fourth after that, of <hi>Iron,</hi> ſtronger then all the former, breaking all the other to pieces, namely, the <hi>Roman,</hi> of long continuance under many forms of Government, but eſpecially long in the feet and toes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all the Popes time, with the ten crowned horns, as appeared more to <hi>Daniel</hi> a Jew, Chap. 7. unto which the Kingdome which the God of heaven would ſet up in the Stone cut out of the mountain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, ſhould ſucceed, which ſhould never be deſtroyed, but ſhould break in pieces and contume the four former Kingdoms, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a great mountain filling the whole earth it ſelf; and ſhould ſtand for ever, though the ſtone was long in beating them in pieces before it became ſuch a mountain filling the whole earth.</p>
               <p>But in Chap. 7. <hi>Daniel</hi> a Jew in the firſt year of <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> hath an other dream,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Daniels</hi> firſt Prophetical Viſion.</note> further ſetting forth all the ſaid M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>narchies, in a Viſion of four Beaſts riſing out of the Sea, upon the ſtriving of the four winds of heaven, again ſetting forth the four ſaid Kingdoms: the firſt like a Lyon, having Eagles wings, to wit, the high ſoaring <hi>Babilonian,</hi> which was brought down in <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> Chap. 7.4. But the ſecond like to a devouring Bear, with three ribs in the mouth,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102104:4"/>conceived to be <hi>Media, Perſia</hi> and <hi>Babilon;</hi> which laſt was taken by <hi>Darius</hi> and <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in whom the <hi>Median</hi> and <hi>Terſian</hi> Kingdome began.</p>
               <p>The third was like a Leopard, having on the back four wings, having alſo four heads, and Dominion was given to it; whereby is decyph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red the <hi>Grecian</hi> Monarchy begun by <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, who like a Leopard was ſwift in catching the prey, of whom alſo it may be ſaid, <hi>Vini, Vidi, Vici.</hi> I came, I ſaw, I overcame; whoſe four Heads or Captains cruelly with their ſucceſſors, chiefly devoured the Jews: which four heads appeared to be four Command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, entring upon <hi>Alexanders</hi> Dominion when he died, <hi>viz. Caſſander</hi> head of <hi>Macedonia, Antigonus</hi> of <hi>Aſia, Seleuchus</hi> of <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Ptolomy</hi> of <hi>Egypt.</hi> But the fourth Beaſt namely, the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchie, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw in the night, Viſions exceeding dreadful, terrible and ſtrong, with iron teeth (their Commanders) and nails of braſs (their Senate) that devoured and brake in pieces and ſtamped the reſidue with the feet of it, and was diverſe from all the beaſts that were before it, and had ten horns: And while <hi>Daniel</hi> conſidered the horn, there came up among them a little horn in appearance at firſt, before whom there were three of the firſt horns pluckt up by the roots; and behold in this horn were eyes, like the eyes of a man, and a mouth ſpeaking great things: thoſe ten horns, one that ſtood by expounded, <hi>v.</hi> 16. to <hi>Dan.</hi> v. 24. to be ten Kings, that ſhould ariſe out of that fourth Kingdome, and that other, to wit, the little horn that ſhould ariſe after them, or behind them (for the ten Kings were to ariſe at one hour with the beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.) who being diverſe from the ten, ſhould ſubdue three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which according to Mr. <hi>Mide,</hi> were the <hi>Lumbards,</hi> the <hi>Franks</hi> and the <hi>Greeks,</hi> ſubdued by the Pope, who during his time, times and the dividing of a time, that is for the ſpace of 1260 days of years, ſhould wear out the Saints of the moſt high, and think to change times and laws, the Saints being ſo long given into his hands, v. 25. But then the ancient of days executed his fiery and ſevere judgment upon that little horn that ſpake great things, with his ten and ten times ten thouſand, by the fiery ſtreams that came from before him, till the beaſt was ſtain, and his body was deſtroyed and given to the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing flame, verſe 9.10.11. the ſame expounded again, verſe 20.21, 22.</p>
               <p>But verſe 13. <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw one like the Son of man come in the clouds of heaven who came to the ancient of days, and they brought him near before him (which probably) will be done by the faithful prayers of the Saints) whereupon was given him Dominion, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102104:5"/>and a Kingdom, that all People, Nations and Languages ſhould ſerve him; and his Dominion is an everlaſting Dominion, which ſhall not paſs away, and his Kingdom that which ſhall not be deſtroyed, as the little Horns or Beaſts was, <hi>v.</hi> 21, 22. who made war with the Saints, and prevailed againſt them, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. but yet onely until the ancient of days came, that Judgment was given to the Saints, and that they poſſeſſed the Kingdom, which was the Kingdom of the Moſt High, whoſe Kingdom ſhould be an everlaſting Kingdom, and all Dominions or Rulers ſhould ſerve and obey him, <hi>v</hi> 27. and that (as there is ſaid) All Kingdoms under the whole Heaven.</p>
               <p>Again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Daniels</hi> ſecond Prophetical Viſion.</note> chap. 8. in the third year of <hi>Belſhazzar, Daniel</hi> had another Viſion concerning the ſecond and third Oppreſſors of the <hi>Jews,</hi> after the times of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> were out, namely, of the Ram of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and the He-Goat of <hi>Grecia</hi> ſucceſſively, until the liſt period of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Perſecution, called the time of the end, and the laſt end of the indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the Angel <hi>Gabriel, v.</hi> 17, 19. &amp; 20, 21. now the Rams, or <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Kings two Horns, were the Kingdoms of <hi>Media</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> againſt whom the He-Goat of <hi>Grecia</hi> came ſo ſwiftly, that he is ſaid not to touch the ground, or none in the earth touched him; but in his chollar came cloſe to the Ram, and caſt him down, and ſtamped upon him; and that notable Horn between his eyes, appears to be <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, whom Stories report not to have been willing to take any offers of Peace, or tearms of Agreement, or tenders of Marriage with the <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings Daughter, but with indignation rejected all, ſaying, The World could not endure two Soveraigns, or chief Kings; but when he was ſtrong, he was broken; and after ſix years, his Four ſaid Commanders, called four notable Horns, <hi>v.</hi> 8, came in his room, and out of one of them, namely, <hi>Seleuchus Nicanor,</hi> by deſcent came that little Horn which waxed exceeding great towards the South, and towards the Eaſt, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the pleaſant Land; which little Horn was <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> who grew great towards <hi>Egypt,</hi> and towards the Eaſt, where the <hi>Perſian</hi> Ram aroſe; and towards the pleaſant Land, where his rage was greatly manifeſt, <hi>v.</hi> 10, 11, 12. againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> who by reaſon of encreaſe of tranſgreſſions, had power given him to afflict them greatly, and do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hainous things againſt their Laws and VVorſhip, magnifying himſelf againſt the Prince of the Hoſt, ſo that by his means the daily Sacrifice was taken away, and the place of Gods Sanctuary was caſt down, for the ſpace of Two thouſand three hundred Mornings and Evenings, or One thouſand one hundred and fifty natural days; or, as ſome take them, for the whole number of dayes, which make up Six years, three months, and twenty dayes, which is conceived to begin when <hi>Menclaus</hi> revolted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102104:5"/>to <hi>Gentiliſm,</hi> and many wicked Apoſtates with him; as firſt of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab.</hi> 1.12. whereupon Gods Temple and Worſhip was contemned and neglected, and people revolted, as 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 4.12, to 18. which A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie began in 142 year of the <hi>Greek</hi> Empire, and continued to the 148th year thereof, and the 11th of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 4.52. though the extremity in <hi>Antiochus</hi> own Reign, was but half the time, which ſeemeth more conſonant to <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie, Evenings and Mornings ſignifying natural days, as in the Creation; and though his wickedneſs proſpered for a time, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. yet after that ſhort time he was broken without hands, being ſtricken with a loathſome diſeaſe, dyed miſerably thereof, as ſeems very probable from 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 9.5, 28, though beſides this, a further myſterie ſeems to be intended in this Scripture, namely, the Jews laſt Reſtauration at the end of the 2300 years, from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchy, and all the time of the <hi>Grecian</hi> and <hi>Roman,</hi> to Chriſts appearance, as afterward; we ſhall endeavout to ſhew.</p>
               <p>Again, chap. 9. in the firſt year of <hi>Darius</hi> the <hi>Mede, Daniel</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by Books, <hi>viz.</hi> from the Propheſie of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> of the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years of the Captivity of the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> as is recorded <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.12. and 29.10. which then drew towards an end; he ſet himſelf by prayers, ſupplications, and faſtings with ſack-cloth and aſhes, to ſeek Gods face for himſelf and his people, <hi>v.</hi> 4.20. whereupon at the time of the Evening-Oblation, the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> came again ſwiftly flying, and touched him, and made known unto <hi>Daniel</hi> what ſhould be done by Gods determinate counſel, after ſeventy Weeks of years, that is 490 years, upon his people, and the holy City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to finiſh tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to make an end of ſins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, and to bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs, and to ſeal the Viſion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and to annoint the Moſt Holy, <hi>v.</hi> 21, 24. ſo that the ſeventy years ſuffering in bondage, ſhould not onely be recompenced with the building of the City, which ſhould remain ſeven times ſeventy years, but ſhould have thoſe glorious Mercies of Mercies to be acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpliſhed in the Meſſiah, which made the beauty of that ſecond Houſe much more glorious then the firſt built by King <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which myſtical ſetting them down, though prophane perſons neither underſtood nor regarded, yet Gods faithful ſervants that would ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, might find them ſuitable to their Jubilies and Prophetical days, and be comforted in them, as by Gods Oracles, rather then if it had been plainly ſaid, after 490 years, in <hi>v.</hi> 25. the former whole number of Seventy Weeks are diſtinguiſhed firſt into ſeaven Weeks, or 49 years from the Edict of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in his firſt year, for their return from Captivity,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102104:6"/>wherein was re-edified <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the ſixth of <hi>Darius Longimanus,</hi> ſecond Son to <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis,</hi> by <hi>Heſter,</hi> in whoſe ſix years the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was built; which being begun in the third year of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> was forty ſix years in building, according to the <hi>Jews</hi> account, by ſome thus rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned; <hi>Cyrus</hi> and <hi>Cambiſes</hi> 9. <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis</hi> 14. <hi>Xerxes</hi> 20. <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> or as ſome, <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus</hi> 6. which ſeems agreeable to the Propheſie. 2dly, Of the 62 weeks, or 434 years following, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in appears, chap. 8. and chap. 11. many remarkable things befell the <hi>Jews;</hi> which 62 Weeks brought in the Meſſiah, and laſted towards the end of his private life; and the one week of the laſt, finiſhed the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt, and begins both the calling of the Gentiles, and rejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Jews, as may be ſupplied from <hi>v.</hi> 27. But in <hi>v.</hi> 26. he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declares the deſtruction of the City and Temple by the <hi>Romans</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Veſpatian:</hi> and after in <hi>v.</hi> 27. ſpeaks, how the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor ſhould make the Sacrifice and Oblation to ceaſe, which was not all done ſuddenly,
<note place="margin">Of which ſaith <hi>Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Judae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and at once, but by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> three diſtinct degrees remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably; though the beginning thereof, then done by <hi>Ceſar,</hi> was in the end of that one laſt Week; for after that woful deſtraction and captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by <hi>Veſpatian</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> they ſought again in oppoſition to Chriſt, to ſet up their Typical Worſhip there. Again, their City was afterwards taken about 130 years after Chriſts incarnation, and the Temple ruined by <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor. And when they had ſet up their ſaid Worſhip again under, or by the Oak in <hi>Mamre, Conſtantine</hi> the Great drave them thence. And laſtly, Moſt remarkably and wonderfully was their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize of building their Temple, diſappointed, when that wicked Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate the Emperor <hi>Julian,</hi> in oppoſition to Chriſts Religion, did not onely ſet up variety of wicked Heatheniſh Abominations, but encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the <hi>Jews</hi> to build their Temple at the publike Charge, which with great endeavours and coſts was ſet upon; but when the ſtones of the old Foundation were digged up, and they went about to lay a new Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by Earth-quakes, Fire, and terrible ſigns of Gods indignation againſt them, many were deſtroyed which were employed about that work, and their very tools and Inſtruments melted and conſumed by the fire, the ſtones laid for foundations, violently caſt up, which occaſioned <hi>Cyrill</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to ſay, Now was fulfilled the prediction of our Saviour, <hi>That not one ſtone ſhould be left upon another, that ſhould not be thrown down.</hi> Which ſeems to be the true Epocha of thoſe 1290 days of years, ſpoken of Ch. 12.11. which probably end before that 45 years preceding Chriſts appearance, as by v. 12. and v. 1. of the ſame Chapter may appear. But of theſe in their due place.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102104:6"/>
               <p>But it is further added in <hi>v.</hi> 27. the latter part of it: And for the overſpreading of Abomination, he ſhall make it deſolate, even until the conſummation, and that determined ſhall be poured upon the deſolate, that is, during the time of the Gentiles, to be fulfilled, as ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.24. which appears to contain all the time of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and the <hi>Jews</hi> diſperſion ever ſince, until their calling about theſe times of ours, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen they are to begin their ſpiritual and civil reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhall end (as was hinted, and may further from Cap. 12. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear) in a glorious and bleſſed ſtate, by the free and rich mercy of their God, and the God of their Fathers, in reſpect both of their ſouls and outward condition, according to the many great promiſes God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and then to be fulfilled to them, their children, and their childrens children for ever, through all the Reign of Chriſt the thouſand years with his Saints on earth, and thenceforth perfect bleſſedueſs to all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>Daniel</hi> in the third year of <hi>Gyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> Chap. 10,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Danids</hi> fourth Prophetical Viſion.</note> 11, 12. had another Viſion, having mourned three full weeks, and ſaw a glorious perſon appearing to him by the River <hi>Hiddekel,</hi> when his Companions fled for fear (though they ſaw not the Viſion) and <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> had no ſtrength nor comelineſs left in him, till he was afterwards raiſed and ſtrengthned, when the Angel made known to him the things that were to come to paſs in the latter dayes: Whereupon Chap. 11. he had the three Earthly Kingdoms then to come, before Chriſts appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſet before him: But firſt briefly of the two former of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> and <hi>Grecia,</hi> I ſay briefly in reſpect of what was ſhewed him in chap. 8. but after more fully of the proceedings of the <hi>Greek</hi> Kingdom divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Two Branches, and moſt largely of the laſt wicked Tyrant <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus Epiphanes,</hi> until he was quelled by the <hi>Romans,</hi> Chap. 11. v. 30.</p>
               <q>Ver. 2. <hi>And now will I ſhew thee the truth. Behold, there ſhall ſtand up yet three Kings in Perſia, and the fourth ſhall be far richer than they all; and by his ſtrength, through his riches, he ſhall ſtir up all againſt the Realm of Grecia.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Onely in <hi>v.</hi> 2. is ſpoken of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Kingdom, in which after Three Kings, to wit, <hi>Cyrus, Cambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis,</hi> ſhould a Fourth, namely, <hi>Xerxes,</hi> ſucceed, richer than them all, who by his ſtrength ſhould ſtir up all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Grecia.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>V. 3, 4. <hi>And a mighty King ſhall ſtand up, that ſhall rule with great Dominion, and do according to his will. And when he ſhall ſtand up, his Kingdom ſhall be broken, and ſhall be divided towards the four winds of Heaven, and not to his poſterity, nor according to his dominion which he ruled; for his Kingdom ſhall be pluckt up, even for others beſides thoſe.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>But then v. 3, and 4. that great <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> whoſe Kingdom ſhould be divided towards
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102104:7"/>the four winds, to his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, as was ſhewed, Cap. 8. not to his poſterity, which after was part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Two, the Kings of the Scuth, namely <hi>Egypt;</hi> and of the North, namely <hi>Syria;</hi> the Wars of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> with the <hi>Perſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> being ſhewed to <hi>Daniel</hi> in Chap. 8. now here was ſhewed to him thoſe that followed in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> who in thoſe times afflicted th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Jews</hi> that lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, by the ſpoil and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of their Armies.</p>
               <q>Ver. 5. <hi>And the King of the South ſhall be ſtrong, and one of his Princes, and he ſhall be ſtrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, and have dominion; his dominion ſhall be a great dominion.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>The King of the South, <hi>v.</hi> 5. is conceived to be <hi>Ptolomeus Lagi</hi> of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and that one of his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces there named, is conceived to be <hi>Seleuchus Nicanor,</hi> who had <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> with the Dominions which he added of <hi>Antigonus</hi> and and <hi>Lyſimachus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Ver. 6. <hi>And in the end of years they ſhall join themſelves together, for the Kings daughter of the ſouth ſhall come to the King of the north to make an agreement; but ſhe ſhall not retain the power of the arm, neither ſhall he ſtand, nor his arm; but ſhe ſhall be given up, and they that brought her, and he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gather, and he that ſtrengthned her in theſe times.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>And v. 6. The two Sons of <hi>Pto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomeus Lagi, Philadelphus</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gas,</hi> contended about the Title of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> vvhen <hi>Antiochus Soter,</hi> Son to <hi>Seleuchus,</hi> aided <hi>Megas,</hi> to vvhom he had before married his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vvhich vvas a bone of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betvveen <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria;</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe vvhich, <hi>Ptolomy Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> married his daughter <hi>Berncie</hi> to <hi>Antiochus Theos,</hi> Son to <hi>Antiochus Soter:</hi> Which Marriage, vvith the ill ſucceſs thereof, is the ſubject of ver. 6. For <hi>Theos</hi> had another Wife <hi>Laodice,</hi> by vvhom he had tvvo Sons, <hi>Seleuchus Callinchus,</hi> and <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Hierax,</hi> vvho took ill their Mothers Divorce, and cauſeleſs reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; vvhereupon they took the firſt opportunity, to cut off <hi>Bernice</hi> and her young Son, vvith all her Train that came vvith her out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and that in deſpight of vvhat her Husband <hi>Theos,</hi> or Father <hi>Philadelphus</hi> could do for her reſcue.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102104:7"/>
               <p>This King of <hi>Egypt Ptolomeus Philadelphus</hi> ſo called, for marrying his own ſiſter, was exceeding rich, and a great warriour; ſtudious of learning, by whoſe procurement the Septuagint tranſlation was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and his daughter <hi>Bernicee,</hi> for her great dowry was ſtiled <hi>Pher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophoras.</hi> But the King of the North here of <hi>Syria,</hi> was <hi>Antiochus Theos</hi> for taking Divine honour to be ſtiled God, after <hi>Laodice</hi> ſeeing her husband <hi>Theos</hi> his inconſtancy, poiſoned him, and to promote her ſon <hi>Callinicus</hi> to the Kingdome.</p>
               <q>Verſe 7. <hi>But out of a branch of her root, ſhall one ſtand up in his eſtate, which ſhall come with an army, and ſhall enter into the fortreſs of the King of the north, and ſhall deal againſt them, and ſhall prevail:</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Then <hi>v.</hi> 7. The brother of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> before ſlain, namely, <hi>Ptolomy Evergetes</hi> called a bud of her root, in revenging of his ſiſters butche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, prevailed againſt <hi>Egypt,</hi> haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding <hi>Callinicus</hi> his whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who ſucceeds his Father <hi>Theos.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Ver. 8. <hi>And ſhall alſo carry captives into Egypt their gods with their Princes, and with their precious Veſſels of Silver, and of Gold, and he ſhall continue more years then the King of the North.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Ptolomy</hi> hearing of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny at home, left his Conqueſt of <hi>Syria,</hi> and returned with his great Booty of 2500 captivated Idols; but <hi>Callinicus</hi> dyed of a fall from his Horſe, the refore ſaid <hi>[not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long]</hi> and his Brother <hi>Hierax</hi> after Civil broyles, was ſlain by a Troop of Robbers, So ended both thoſe Murtherers.</p>
               <q>Ver. 9. <hi>So the King of the ſouth ſhall come into his Kingdom, and ſhall return into his own Land.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 9. <hi>Energetes</hi> upon his return home to <hi>Egypt,</hi> repreſſed the Commotions <hi>[and ſo returned]</hi> as is ſaid, unto his Kingdom.</p>
               <q>Ver. 10. <hi>But his ſons ſhall be ſtirred up, and ſhall aſſemble a multitude of great forces; and one ſhall certainly come and overflow, and paſs thorow; then ſhall he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and be ſtirred up even to his Fortreſs.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 10. The two Sons of <hi>Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus,</hi> to wit, <hi>Seleuchus Serannus,</hi> and <hi>Antiochus Megas,</hi> could not endure that <hi>Ptolomy Philopator</hi> that killed his Father <hi>Energetes,</hi> ſhould poſſeſs any part of <hi>Syria</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their noſes, muſtered up what power they could; but <hi>Cerannus</hi> being poyſoned, <hi>Antiochus</hi> warred with <hi>Ptolomies</hi> Captains, who over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Attalus,</hi> and drew <hi>Theodolus</hi> to reſign <hi>Syria</hi> unto <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102104:8"/>to help him againſt his own Maſter, <hi>Ptolomy;</hi> ſo he overflowed <hi>Syria,</hi> and ſet upon <hi>Philopators</hi> ſtrong holds of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Ver. 11. <hi>And the King of the South ſhall be moved with choler, and ſhall come forth and fight with him, even with the King of the North; and he ſhall ſet forth a great multitude, but the multitude ſhall be given into his hand.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Ver. 11. But <hi>Antiochus</hi> beſieged <hi>Raphia,</hi> was overcome by <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pator</hi>'s Army, and his great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes partly ſlain, and partly capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated.</p>
               <q>Ver. 12. <hi>And when he hath taken away the multitude, his heart ſhall be liſted up, and he ſhall coſt down many ten thouſands, but he ſhall not be ſtrengthned by it.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 12. <hi>Ptolomy Philopator</hi> being purfed up, exerciſed great cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> and would have gone into the Holy of Holies, whom the High-Prieſt reſiſted; whereupon he made cruel Edicts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and put many to cruel deaths, as 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 3, &amp; 4 chap. but was given up to unclean luſts, had a Male-Concubine, one <hi>Agathocles,</hi> killed his Wife and Siſter, ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtruck with death, and left his young Son to the tuition of that vile <hi>Agathocles;</hi> whereupon divers parts under him rebelled; and then <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochns</hi> having made preparation more ſtrongly, invades his Sons Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
               <q>Ver. 13. <hi>For the King of the North ſhall return, and ſhall ſet forth a multitude greater than the former, and ſhall certainly come (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter certain years) with a great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and with much riches.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 13. That Child of four years old, <hi>Ptolomeus Epiphanes,</hi> the Nobles ſtomached to be left under the laſcivious <hi>Agathocles,</hi> encouraged <hi>Antiochus</hi> expedition [after certain years as is ſaid] But the <hi>Romans</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken the tuition of that young King, gave him a rub by an Embaſſage, to forbear the Territories of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi> which notwithſtanding, after certain years, he did invade <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Ver. 14. <hi>And in thoſe times there ſhall many ſtand up againſt the King of the South; alſo the Robbers of thy people ſhall exalt themſelves to eſtabliſh the Viſion, but they ſhall fall.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 14. But the <hi>Jews</hi> finding then content under <hi>Antiochus,</hi> took part with him againſt the Emperor; but divers <hi>Jews</hi> having built a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in <hi>Egypt</hi> to ſet up their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip there, were devoured by <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> his Army.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102104:8"/>
               <q>Ver. 15. <hi>So the King of the north ſhall come, and caſt up a Mounts and take the moſt fenced Cities, and the arms of the ſouth ſhall not withſtand, neither his choſen peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, neither ſhall there be any ſtrength to withſtand.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 15. <hi>Antiochus</hi> makes a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond expedition againſt <hi>Egypt,</hi> with all Warlike preparation, and gave it a great overthrow, as he had had a great foyl at <hi>Raphia</hi> before.</p>
               <q>Ver. 16. <hi>But he that cometh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, ſhall do according to his own will, and none ſhall ſtand before him; and he ſhall ſtand in the glorious Land, which by his hand ſhall be conſumed.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 16. <hi>Antiochus</hi> being helped before by the <hi>Jews,</hi> comes among them with his Souldiers, that he might have ſuccour near him; but thoſe Souldiers did ſo waſt their Land without reſpect to friend or foe, that <hi>Antiochus</hi> his peace, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to them little better than <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> Hoſtility.</p>
               <q>Verſe 17. <hi>He ſhall alſo ſet his face to enter with the ſtrength of his whole kingdom, and upright ones with him: thus ſhall he do, and he ſhall give him the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of women corrup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing her: but ſhe ſhall not ſtand on his ſide; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be for him.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 17. <hi>Antiochus</hi> thought of a third expedition into <hi>Egypt,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover what he had loſt, and though ſtrongly prepared and begun with hopeful ſucceſſe, yet was ſtopped by the <hi>Roman</hi> Protectors of <hi>Epiphanes</hi> their pupill: But <hi>Antiochus</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended amity, and to give his daughter to <hi>Epiphanes,</hi> and thought to corrupt her, to deſtroy her husband, which beautiful <hi>Cleopatra</hi> the daughter of women would not do.</p>
               <q>Verſe 18. <hi>After this ſhall he turn his face unto the Iſles, and ſhall take many; but a Prince for his own behalf ſhall cauſe the reproach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffered by him, to ceaſe; without his own repreach he ſhall cauſe it to turn upon him.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 18. <hi>Antiochus</hi> ill bearing two affronts done him by the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> in <hi>Egypt:</hi> now to ſhew his Lordlineſs, invades <hi>Grecia,</hi> and ſpoils the countreys of <hi>Helleſpont Cherſoneſus Eubojea</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Called Iſles, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.45.</note>, formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Roman</hi> title, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in firſt ſucceeding, well he mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the <hi>Romane</hi> terrour: but ſmarted by them afterward: whereupon [the Prince] (not yet being at the height of their Kingdome) that is the <hi>Roman</hi> State [for his own behalf] (not now as formerly, for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102104:9"/>
                  <hi>Epiphanes, v.</hi> 12. returned his reproach upon him, being thrice van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed by them by Sea and Land, they forced him to ſurrender what he had won by Wars in <hi>Grecia,</hi> and defray their Charges, and deliver to them his Ships and Elephants which they required, and to give twenty Hoſtages, to pay a huge ſum of moneys for twelve years, and one of the Hoſtages to be his Son.</p>
               <q>Ver. 19. <hi>Then he ſhall turn his face towards the fort of his own Land; but he ſhall ſtumble and fall, and not be found.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Antiochus</hi> returning to his ſtrong-hold of <hi>Syria,</hi> being to pay 1500 Talents laid on him, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted for ſupply to rob the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Juppiter Belus</hi> in <hi>Perſia;</hi> whereupon the Barbarous people tumultuoſly ſlew him; ſo <hi>[he ſtumbled and fell, not being found.]</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Ver. 20. <hi>Then ſhall stand up in his eſtate a raiſer of Taxes in the glory of the Kingdom; but within few dayos he ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, neither in anger, nor in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 20. Then unto <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Great, ſucceeded <hi>Seleuchus Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopator,</hi> his Fathers Darling, in his Kingdom of <hi>Syria,</hi> who to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his pomp, laid heavy Taxes on his Subjects, and attempted by his Captain <hi>Helioderus,</hi> to rob the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and ſhortly after was poyſoned by the ſame Captain.</p>
               <q>Ver. 21. <hi>And in his eſtate ſhall ſtand up a vile perſon, to whom they ſhall not give the Horour of the Kingdom; but he ſhall come in pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eably, and obtain the Kingdom by flatteries.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 21. Then ſucceeded <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Epiphanes,</hi> (or as ſome <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> the Vile) who was left an Hoſtage with the <hi>Romans,</hi> by his Father, and now <hi>Demetrius</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Son, the Heir of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, was to be Hoſtage in his room; but before his return, the Heir was poyſoned (as was thought) by his means, by the aforeſaid <hi>Heliodorus.</hi> This <hi>Antiochus</hi> was reſiſted in the life time of the Heir <hi>Demetrius;</hi> but he wound himſelf in by pleading the Heir was unable to weild ſo troublous a ſtate, and ſo would undertake his Tuition, and ſo by flattering, gulled the Nobles.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102104:9"/>
               <q>Ver. 22. <hi>And with the arms of a Flood ſhall they be overflown from before him, and ſhall be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: yea alſo the power of the Covenant.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 22. Then by three main aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted in the old quarrel with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi> Firſt, he took occaſion by the minority of <hi>Ptolomy Philoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> ſon to <hi>Ptolomy Epiphanes,</hi> ſon to <hi>Cleopatra, Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> his Siſter, to invade <hi>Egypt</hi> with great Forces, where he overthrew <hi>Philomators</hi> two Captains with a ſtorm or flood of diſcomfiture. The Prince of the Covenant ſeemed to be <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon,</hi> who upon the former Overthrow, was the principal Actor in a League between him and the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> whereupon he having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into <hi>Egypt</hi> firſt, took away <hi>Tryphon</hi> the chief Witneſs of the League, the better to conceal his Treachery.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Ver. 23, 24. <hi>And after the League made with him, he ſhall work deceitfully; for he ſhall come up, and ſhall become ſtrong with a ſmall people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ver. 24. <hi>He ſhall enter peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly even upon the fatteſt places of the Province, and he ſhall do that which his Fathers have not done, nor his Fathers Fathers; he ſhall ſcatter among them the prey and ſpoil, and riches; yea, and he ſhall forecaſt his devices againſt the ſtrong Holds, even for a time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 23, 24 This <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Vile, regarded not the League he had made, but entring upon <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> ſcattering handfuls of money to win the Vulgar, which he had got amongſt them, and practiſed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices againſt the Strong-holds of <hi>Memphis</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Cities, by ſowing diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Philometor</hi> the elder, and <hi>Phiſochon</hi> the younger brother, whoſe the two ſaid Cities were; but (as ſaith the Text) it was but for a while, the elder brother by the Mediation of a Siſter to them both, prevented that device.</p>
               <q>Ver. 25. <hi>And he ſhall ſtir up his Power and his Courage againſt the King of the ſouth, with a great ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and the King of the ſouth ſhall be ſtirred up to battel with a very great and mighty army, but he ſhall not ſtand, for they ſhall forecaſt devices againſt him.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 25. As the ſtrength of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> the Vile, at firſt was Policy and Devices; ſo in this his ſecond Expedition, he ſtirred up all the ſtrength of <hi>Syria</hi> to try by War.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102104:10"/>
               <q>Ver. 26. <hi>Yea, they that feed of the portion of his meat, ſhall deſtroy him, and his army ſhall over flow, and many ſhall fall down ſlain.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 26. Yet the Courtiers of <hi>Philometor</hi> ſecretly plot with this <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Vile, againſt all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and engagements to the King, their Families, and all Intereſts.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 27. <hi>And both theſe Kings hearts ſhall be to do miſchief, and they ſhall ſpeak lies at one Table; but it ſhall not proſper; for yet the end ſhall be at the time appointed.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 27. After the Battle fought, the two Kings parley about a Truce wherein each ſtrives to outreach the other; and <hi>Antiochus</hi> was Royally feaſted by <hi>Philometor,</hi> which were but for a time diſſembled, till Gods time came.</p>
               <q>Ver. 28. <hi>Then ſhall he return into his own Land with great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and his heart ſhall be againſt the holy Covenant; and he ſhall do exploits, and return to his own Land.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 28. <hi>Antiochus</hi> having got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten much Treaſure upon the Truce, and robbing the Temple of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> which paid him Tribute for two years reprieve of the <hi>Jews,</hi> many of which he corrupted afore-hand, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1.21, to 24.</p>
               <q>Ver. 29. <hi>At the time appointed he ſhall return, and come toward the ſouth; but it ſhall not be as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, or as the latter.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>Ver. 29. So after the ſaid two years, he invades <hi>Egypt</hi> the third time, beſieging the Royal City <hi>Memphis,</hi> which he ſoon after took, and drave <hi>Philometor</hi> to flye for his life to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which as he went to beſiege, <hi>Popilius</hi> arrives on an Embaſſie from <hi>Rome,</hi> and diſcharges <hi>Antiochus</hi> from any further inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on <hi>Philometors</hi> Countrey, whoſe Tuition the Senate and people of <hi>Rome</hi> had undertaken. But while <hi>Antiochus</hi> was complementing of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius,</hi> and other <hi>Romans</hi> of his old Acquaintance, the Noble <hi>Roman</hi> makes a Circle in the Sand, and charges him to return Anſwer before he went out of it; whereunto he obeyed. [Now was the time of the end of the Wars with <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> mentioned v. 27.]</p>
               <q>Ver. 30. <hi>For the Ships of Chit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ſhall come againſt him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhall be grieved and return, and have indignation againſt the holy Covenant; ſo ſhall he do, he ſhall even return, and have In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence with them that forſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the holy Covenant.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 30. The <hi>Romans</hi> (called the Ships of <hi>Chittim,</hi> for they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver landed at <hi>Alexandria</hi>) came of <hi>Chittim</hi> one of the Sons of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>van, Gen.</hi> 10.4. from whom <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102104:10"/>and all <hi>Italy</hi> was peopled; <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus</hi> having tranſported the <hi>Citians</hi> from the <hi>Greekiſh</hi> Iſlands into <hi>Italy;</hi> and here the wonderful Numberer ſets them forth by the Ships of <hi>Chittim,</hi> that ſo the Jews from <hi>Baalams</hi> Propheſie, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.24. might hence know the riſe and ruine of their laſt great Oppreſſor, the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom. And he had intelligence with ſuch as forſake the Covenant; for many Rebellious <hi>Jews</hi> deſirous to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh Gentiliſm, did privily pack with him againſt their Citie and people, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1.14.</p>
               <q>Ver. 31. <hi>And arms ſhall ſtand on his part, and they ſhall pollute the Sanctuary of ſtrength, and ſhall take away the daily Sacrifice, and they ſhall place the abomination that maketh deſolate.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 31. In his Attempts againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> beſides treacherous Jews, he had Foraign Captains, <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Andronicus,</hi> and <hi>Apollonius,</hi> as 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24. men of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable cruelties to act for him, who having taken the Fort of <hi>Sion,</hi> committed miſerable Maſſacres, without reſpect of Sex or Age, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1.35. and polluted the Temple by blood of Infants, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1.39. Secondly, By their going into the Temple, being ſtrangers, as <hi>Act.</hi> 21.28. Thirdly, To meddle with holy things, <hi>v.</hi> 47. and <hi>v</hi> 54, and 57. ſetting up the Idol <hi>Juppiter Olimpius,</hi> in the Temple, called the Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.34. and God hates Idolatry, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13. and it brings deſolation, for which the Jews were ſo ſadly and ſorely plagued.</p>
               <q>Ver. 32. <hi>And ſuch as do wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly againſt the Covenant, ſhall be corrupt by flatteries; but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that do know their God, ſhall be ſtrong, and do exploits.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 32. Divers Jewes joined with <hi>Antiochus</hi> againſt their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as <hi>Menelaus</hi> vvas guide to <hi>Antiochus</hi> in his robbing the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and vvere more outragious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Brethren, than the very Gentiles, 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 5.15, 23. So <hi>Jaſan Alcimus,</hi> vvho contrary to his Oath betrayed his Brethren, and aided <hi>Bacchides,</hi> 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 7.5, 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the faithful <hi>Aſſideans</hi> Godly zeal in reſiſting Gentiliſm, and cleaving to Gods Worſhip, is recorded 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1.25. vvith their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Exploits of War, as follovvs <hi>v.</hi> 34.</p>
               <q>Ver. 33. <hi>And they that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand among the people, ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct many; yet they ſhall fall by the ſword, and by flame, by capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and by ſpoil many dayes.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 33. The Saints then had ſad Tryals, 1. By the Svvord, 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 5.25. 2dly, Caſt into the fire, or ſcalding, 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 7.34. 3ly, Sold to Gentiles, 2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 5.24. ſpoiled by Robbers, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 1.37, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:11"/>
               <q>Ver. 34. <hi>Now when they ſhall fall, they ſhall be holpen with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle help; but many ſhall cleave to them with flatteries.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 34. The little help was by <hi>Mattathias</hi> and his Sons, <hi>Judas</hi> and his Brethren, who but an handful to <hi>Antiochus</hi> and his Army, yet God proſpered their Attempts to be a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge to their diſtreſſed Brethren, and a vexation to their Enemies, to whom they gave many foiles, 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 2.24, 28, 29, 47. yet were there many falſe Brethren, as <hi>Alcimus</hi> and others.</p>
               <q>Ver. 35. <hi>And ſome of them of underſtanding ſhall fall to try them, and to purge, and to make them white, even to the time of the end, becauſe it is yet for a time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 35. Thus were the Saints tryed by ſufferings from friends and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, to their future honour, in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their faith and conſtancy; and now was the appointed end of <hi>Javans</hi> rage; as in v. 1. was finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Tyranny of <hi>Babel.</hi> And v. 2. contained Four Tyrants of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and their rage finiſhed in <hi>Xerxes</hi> famous overthrow. And the third begins <hi>Javans</hi> firſt Oppreſſor, till <hi>Antiochus the Vile,</hi> whoſe death was ſpoken of Chap. 8. v. 25. which ſeems to be meant by the time of the end in this place, by reaſon the Spirit of God ſeems to end that Kingdom, then called the appointed time for it, when the tryals and temptations of the Saints by his means was finiſhed in that appointed time.</p>
               <q>Ver. 36. <hi>And the King ſhall do according to his will, and he ſhall exalt himſelf, and magnifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above every God, and ſhall ſpeak marvellous things againſt the God of gods, and ſhall proſper, till the indignation be accompliſhed; for that that is determined, ſhall be done.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 36. The King here ſpoken of, is the <hi>Roman</hi> State, who was to proſper unto the end of the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God againſt the Jews, as chap. 9.27. he ſpeaks of this King without diſtinction of North or South, as before (v. 18.) the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> were but the Prince, (v. 30.) he calls them the Ships of <hi>Chittim.</hi> But here the King having the chief power, to whom many Kings ſubmitted and crouched, as the two <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chuſſes,</hi> Father and Son, <hi>Syria</hi>'s ſtouteſt Warriours. <hi>Perſeus</hi> King of <hi>Macodonia,</hi> brought with Wife and Children to trudg after <hi>Emilius</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing Chariot. <hi>Hannibal</hi> flying ſeveral wayes, was ſent for by the <hi>Romans,</hi> and could not be freed from them, but poiſoned himſelf. <hi>Geu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> King of the <hi>Illyrians</hi> felt their terror. So <hi>Pruſias</hi> King of <hi>Bythinia; Eumenes</hi> King of <hi>Pergamus; Ariarathes</hi> King of <hi>Cappadocia; Deiota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:102104:11"/>King of <hi>Galatia; Mithridates</hi> King of <hi>Pontus, &amp;c.</hi> all which felt the <hi>Roman</hi> yoke, or brake their hearts or Kingdoms by reſiſting; and their inſolency hath been as much over the Jews, and above any others; for they made <hi>Judea</hi> a Province, and billetted their Souldiers in every City, and took away all Capital Government by Laws, Offices and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, as <hi>Florus</hi> obſerves, and others; and after <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was made equal to the Earth by <hi>Veſpatian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But their inſolency over earthly Gods, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. hath been ſeen in the <hi>Roman</hi> Antichriſt, for Hiſtory relates at leaſt 20 famous Emperours and Kings trampled under foot by him miſerably &amp;c. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſuch as ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt themſelves in his device of the holy wars, and to act for him in other countreys, &amp;c. Again the Church and State of <hi>Rome</hi> have been manifeſt by blaſphemies, when <hi>Ptolomy</hi> and <hi>Cleopatra</hi> told the Senate, they were more bebolding to them, then to the immortal Gods, they took it ſo: When <hi>Cicero</hi> uttered blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt Gods Religion, as barbarous ſuperſtition, and againſt God himſelf, as unworthy to be owned by the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſince his people the Jews, who profeſſed dependance on him, were overcome; which Blaſphemies were entertained and applauded.</p>
               <p>The Emperor <hi>Tiberius</hi> was deſirous to Authorize Chriſt amongſt the number of the <hi>Roman</hi> gods; but was reſiſted by the Senate, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it belonged unto them to make or unmake Deities as they pleaſed.</p>
               <p>But this Blaſphemy is more palpable on the <hi>Roman</hi> Antichriſt, who challengeth to be ſtiled God, and that by the Emperor himſelf; and his Diſciples ſtile him, Our Lord God the Pope, a certain Deity on Earth, and the greateſt Deity on Earth, and by open allowance.</p>
               <p>And though this Fourth Tyrant over the Jews was to continue long in the ſeveral Heads of that State, and the Pope is the 8th or of the 7th, and alſo that Turkiſh State over the Jews; yet when Gods people ſhall be raiſed from the duſt of diſperſion and bondage, both Pope and Turk will at once be deſtroyed, and caſt into the ſtreams of Fire and Brimſtone, iſſuing from the Ancient of Days.</p>
               <p>Yet it ſeemeth to me the 36 Verſe is rather to be reſtrained to the former times of the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, under the Senate, Kings, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and other Governors before the Popes time, and ſuiteth well there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and it is remarkable, That the Spirit of Chriſt teacheth the Prophet uſually to ſet down his Propheſies and Viſions, according to the order of accompliſhment, except in occaſional explications, as Chap. 7, 8. and 12. in ſome things; yet Idolatry, Blaſphemy and Tyranny, are ſuch ſpirits as have run in the blood, through the whole Body of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monſter.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102104:12"/>
               <p>And that general note of the long continuance thereof, the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom ſhall proſper, till the indignation ſhall be accompliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that is, to the end of the Jews diſperſion and bondage, and coming of Chriſt, Cap. 12.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Ver. 37, 38, 39. <hi>Neither ſhall he regard the God of his Fathers, nor the deſire of women, nor regard any God; for he ſhall magnifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf above all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ver. 38. <hi>But in his eſtate ſhall he honor the God of forces, and a God whom his Fathers knew not, ſhall he honour with gold and ſilver, and with precious ſtones, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ver. 39. <hi>Thus ſhall he do in the moſt ſtrong holds with a ſtrange god, whom he ſhall acknowledg and encreaſe with glory; and he ſhall cauſe them to rule over many, and ſhall divide the Land for gain.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>But <hi>Ver.</hi> 37, 38, 39. ſeems evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to belong to the Popes time in a ſpecial manner, his not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the God of his Fathers, ſets forth the Antichriſtian Hypocriſie, <hi>ſub nomine Chriſti militant, contra Chriſtum,</hi> they pretend for God and Chriſt, but intend all for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; not as the Apoſtles and firſt <hi>Roman</hi> Chriſtians, that ſo regarded their God, that with heart and hand not onely in well-doing, but in ſelf-denial and ſufferings, to the loſs of Eſtate, Life, Liberty and all, they ſtedfaſtly clave unto him. But now all the honor of Chriſts Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Prieſtly and Kingly Offices are taken (in effect) from him, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to the Pope, and eſpecially in reſpect of their Breaden Gods I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, as might be ſhewed, and particularly follows in the next verſe; and how much the Papiſts diſallow lawful Marriage, and reproach it, [here called the deſire of Women] is too manifeſt both by their Doctrines and Practiſes; and as for Atheiſtical Blaſphemies, their Writings are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominably fraught and filled therewith.</p>
               <p>And how his new-coin'd Breaden God, and what deviſed honor is given to him, what Riches and Ornaments beſtowed upon him, how ſet up in Cities, Kingdoms and Countreys, what promotions go with him, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, what Prohibitions of Traffique, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Perſecuſions, to the Oppoſers of his Worſhip, is too large here to be ſet down.</p>
               <q>Ver. 40. <hi>And at the time of the end ſhall the King of the ſouth puſh at him, and the King of the North come againſt him like a whirlwind with Charets, and with Horſemen, and with many Ships, and he ſhall enter into the countreys, and ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d paſs over.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 40. But that he might not in the time of the end be ſo terrible in Might in the World, as he was grown notorious in wickedneſs in the world, God had appointed to ſend him gradually ſuch a Checkmate thenceforward, to act another part
<pb facs="tcp:102104:12"/>upon the Worlds Stage, that ſhould both reſtrain his Power, and curb his Pride; which was the <hi>Mahumitan</hi> Antichriſt, ariſing out of the bottomleſs pit, as well as the Pope, which to carry on the Perdition of that wicked Iron <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, in two Wo-Trumpets, was to blow out the Wrath and Judgment upon the Eaſtern Empire eſpecially, and to reſtrain the Man of Sin, which otherwiſe might have ſeemed too much like a God on Earth indeed: Firſt, Raiſing the Saracens about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 600. or not long after, to puſh at the Eaſtern <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, by many aſſaults and incurſions, in which both Saracens and Romanized Chriſtians were both, or at leaſt by courſe, the Jews oppreſſors, in the times of thoſe ſuppoſed Holy Wars, but more eſpecially, ſince the Turk came againſt him with his Multitudes, about the year of our Lord 1300, with Chariots and Horſemen, and many Ships; for his hour, and a day, and a month, and a year, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.15. that is, 396 years he ſhould continue to overflow with his Multitudes, and paſs over, is not yet fully compleat.</p>
               <q>Ver. 41. <hi>He ſhall enter alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorious land, and many Countreys ſhall be overthrown; but theſe ſhall eſcape out of his hand, even Edom and Moab, nnd the chief of the children of Ammon.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 41. The Turk ſhould poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs <hi>Judea,</hi> and many other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys ſhould be ſubdued by him; yet <hi>Edom, Moab,</hi> and the chief of the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> ſhould eſcape his hands, where multitudes of the Jews have been ſhattered, wherein (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> obſerves) the Providence of God hath been in that reſpect remarkable, That the Turk hath made compoſition with them, that they might not prey upon the Borders of his Dominions.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Ver. 42, 43. <hi>He ſhall ſtretch forth his hand alſo upon the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, and the Land of Egypt ſhall not eſcape.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ver. 43. <hi>But he ſhall have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the Treaſures of gold and ſilver, and over all the precious things of Egypt; and the Liby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and the Ethiopians ſhall be at his ſteps.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 42, 43. Though <hi>Egypt</hi> held out long againſt the Turks by the help of the <hi>Mamalucks,</hi> yet about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1517. they were ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; when as is ſet forth in this Text, the Turk having taken <hi>Tonumbeias</hi> (their King) captive, before he put him to death, he ſet him on the Rack, to wring out of him where his Treaſure lay, as he did with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Royal Race, and Royal City <hi>Memphis,</hi> to get their hid Treaſures, as the Text ſpeaks; the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byans</hi> and Blackmoors aiding the Turk, and ſupplying him with neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in this War.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:13"/>
               <q>Ver. 44. <hi>But tydings out of the Eaſt, and out of the North ſhall trouble him; therefore he ſhall go forth with great fury to deſtroy, and utterly to make away many.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 44. Thoſe tydings out of the Eaſt appear to be of the Jews, that gather together about 1290 days of years, after the ceaſing of their publike Sacrificing in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtates time, and his ſo pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like ſetting up Heatheniſh Abominations, making deſolate, who before, or then were Eaſt from <hi>Judea,</hi> or to the <hi>Turks;</hi> whoſe gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be to get their own Land, given to their Fathers and their Seed for a poſſeſſion for ever, which they muſt enjoy to the Worlds end. [And out of the North] appears to be the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> carried cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> North from <hi>Judea,</hi> who probably at the ſame time joyn with their Brethren the Jews upon the like deſign; againſt whom the Turk in ruinous rage, will gather force to cut them off utterly.</p>
               <q>Ver. 45. <hi>And he ſhall plant the Tabernacles of his Palace between the Seas, in the glorious Holie Mountain; yet he ſhall come to his end, and none ſhall help him.</hi>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 45. He will go into <hi>Judea,</hi> (here again called the holy Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) to ſecure himſelf, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his part, but ſhall not thereby eſcape his determined ruine at the end of the 6th Trumpet, or ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the 7th whereupon comes Chriſts appearance, as Chap. 12.1. when both Turk and Pope will be deſtroyed, making up the body of the great Myſtical Antichriſt; and all Gods people freed from that Spirit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage.</p>
               <p>So that Chap. 12.1. ſets out the time when, and the perſon by whom the Jews deliverance from their diſperſion and bondage ſhould be begun, with the terror to come upon the World of wicked men, then up, and in great oppoſition of his Church and People, both in Eaſt and Weſt, the Turk being then in the height of his rage againſt the converted Jews, as before; and the Pope about to perfect the Armageddon Battel at the end of the ſixth Viol, when Chriſt with his Armies comes to deſtroy him and them, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. from v. 11, to the end; and <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. towards the latter end; and as in this Chapter it is ſhewed it ſhall be at the end of his time, times, and half a time, when he ſhall have accompliſhed or finiſhed to ſcatter the power of the holy people; when as his time, ſaith the ſame Angel of the Covenant, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. by a ſolemn Oath, his time ſhall be no longer; all which time Chriſt revealed before, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. his Church ſhould be in a Wilderneſs condition; for ſo the wore here (ſcattered) ſeems to imply; being onely hid here and there by Gods Providence, and his accompliſhing of that ſcattering of them, denotes,
<pb facs="tcp:102104:13"/>That then they ſhall come out of that condition; and whereas their power till then was ſcattered, that then they ſhould have a power to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite themſelves, and their enemies not to have any longer power to hold them under, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though as the <hi>Jews</hi> will firſt have a beginning of their Reſurrection, both Spiritual, by Converſion; and Civil, from their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and diſperſion at the end of the 1290 dayes of years, <hi>v.</hi> 11. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably from <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtates time, about <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 366, the moſt probable Epocha of thoſe dayes, which will not be perfected until the 1335 dayes, v. 12, that is, 45 years after, at the ſtanding up of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> their Prince at his appearing: So at the end of the 42 months, or his time, times, and half a time, when the laſt finiſhing Witneſſes ſhall ariſe again, there will be a time for the gathering of the Pope, with his Antichriſtian Armies, to the Battel of the great God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. before he be wholly caſt into the Lake of fire, together with the Turk (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably) but all the faithful Jews ſhall be delivered, whoſe names are found written in the Book of Life, when will be their great and moſt National Converſion, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 2, 3. Set forth the different condition of ſeveral ſorts of Jews, from their firſt awakening at the end of 1290 dayes, to the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their more general Call, as v. 11, 12. and what temporal, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, or conſequently eternal glory or diſgrace will befall the ſeveral ſorts amongſt them, according to their faithfulneſs in cleaving to Chriſt in their troubles, or prevailing with their Brethren to adhere to Chriſts Righteouſneſs alone againſt all Jewiſh or Heatheniſh Seducements, wherewith probably they may be aſſaulted; or the contrary, as any ſhall be unfaithful or revolters, being ſeduced in the 45 years following, either by their falſe revolting Brethren, or by the Turkiſh Tyranny or flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of ſuch ariſing, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> is informed, Chap. 37. which is here peculiarly applied to <hi>Daniels</hi> people the Jews, and to many of them, not all, who are turned to righteouſneſs of Juſtification, which God will accept, which they owned not before, with many other things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable from the Text, as the natural ſcope of it will ſhew.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 4, and 9, is the ſealing of this Viſion from <hi>Daniels</hi> time, until the time of the end, as again <hi>Daniel</hi> was further informed, v. 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. the latter end, and v. 6, 7. there ſeems to be two diſtinct Notes and Characters given of the time of the end, under which was u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that very ſame expreſſion, Chap. 11.40. namely, of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors and Popes dayes, which <hi>Daniel</hi> when he had heard, ſaith, v. 8. he underſtood them not; whereof two Reaſons ſeem obſervable from the Text, Firſt, That they did not directly concern <hi>Daniels</hi> people.
<pb facs="tcp:102104:14"/>Secondly, He is again in the next particularly told, They were then ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed till the ſaid time of the end, Chap. 11.40. and Chap. 12.9.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe Notes or Characters ſeems to be of the Primative times from the Apoſtles, before Antichriſts Forty two Months, or time, times and half a time began, namely, <hi>[That many ſhould run to and fro, and knowledg ſhould be encreaſed]</hi> which appears to be a Mark of thoſe times wherein either the Apoſtles and other faithful Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, by their travels, and preaching, and diſperſions, and perſecutions, and ſuch like means (then) were ſucceſsfully inſtrumental to cauſe the knowledge and profeſſion of the Goſpel of Chriſt to abound, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and by an Emphaſis called Knowledg; being not onely the principal, but the onely neceſſary thing to be known by all men: Or elſe, that many that by ſuch means took up the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, having onely the light and the knowledg thereof, but not the Grace of the Goſpel, might for a time haſten to take up that Profeſſion; but by tentations and perſecutions, be as haſty to run away from the owning of that Profeſſion, according to the changes and turnings of the Affairs of thoſe Primative times.</p>
               <p>And the ſecond Note or Character is more clear (which likewiſe gives further evidence to this) in that it is of the times ſucceeding thoſe primative times, ſtamped with a very evident mark to diſcover them, namely, Antichriſts time, times and half a time, or dividing of a time, as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.14. which v. 5, 6, 7. is ſet forth to <hi>Daniel</hi> in a Viſion, and reſerved, as follows, to be explained by Chriſt himſelf, v. 8, 9. in the time of the end, which he hath done accordingly, <hi>Rev</hi> 10.6, 7. to which purpoſe <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw two perſons on each ſide of the River, v. 5. and one enquires of the other for the end of thoſe Wonders; whereupon the man clothed in white Linen (who probably is the ſame perſon, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.) utters in <hi>Daniels</hi> hearing, the Oath that follows to the like purpoſe, as we before noted.</p>
               <p>But <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12. he gives <hi>Daniel</hi> (that beloved Prophet) two other Marks of the times, more diſcernable to him, as having reference to his own people the Jews (though then particularly hid to him, ſince they were of things to come) namely, The continuance of the <hi>Jews</hi> diſperſion and bondage, after the laſt moſt remarkable taking away of Sacrifice, and ſetting up the Abomination of Deſolation, moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly (as we ſaid before) in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate Emperor's time, about 366, from about which time the 1290 dayes of years are to be counted.</p>
               <p>And ver. 12. ſetteth forth the bleſſed condition of ſuch faithful Jews or Iſraelites, as waited on God in doing their duty, and ſhall ſtill remain ſo doing to the appearing of Chriſt at, or about 1335 dayes of years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:102104:14"/>their firſt awakening, or call from diſperſion and bondage.</p>
               <p>And the ſaid man clothed in white Linnen, having laid down ſome general conſolations for the faithful Sufferers all along thoſe evil times, till the times of the end were paſt (which he had before newly ſpoken of) v. 10 he then concludes with a particular conſolation to <hi>Daniel</hi> concerning his part and lot he was to receive when his people ſhould be delivered, and when <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were to receive the Lot of their Inheritance in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which God had ſworn to give them; and yet his Word witneſſeth (in the dayes of their Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage) they poſſeſſed not a foot of, even then <hi>Daniel</hi> is likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed from Chriſt, that he ſhould then have his own Lot there with them, at the firſt Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. or, as our Saviour calls it, the Reſurrection from the dead, <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.35. which here <hi>Daniel</hi> is taught by him as to his own Intereſt, will then be fulfilled in the end of the dayes, when the aforeſaid evil times are paſt, of which it is ſaid, <hi>Time ſhould be no longer,</hi> Rev. 10.6.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="comparisons">
               <head>The Parallel between <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions and the Book of the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which is meerly a Divine, Myſtical Comment or Expoſition of the two laſt Monarchies, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy and Chriſts: from the time the <hi>Revelation</hi> took place: and firſt of the Parallel, of what concerns the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy in both <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN order unto which ſaid Parallel, we muſt take notice, that the greateſt part of the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt from the beginning of the firſt chapter, ſetting forth the glorious perſon, whom then <hi>John</hi> ſaw, who (as he calls himſelf afterward, and) appears to be the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> therein, in whoſe ſecond comeing the Propheſies reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Monarchy, are to be fulfilled and compleated, being then to be utterly and for ever deſtroyed, and to go into perdition, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 17 is ſaid; from which period he will ſet up his own Kingdom, as chapt. 20. and ſo forward, except what is ſpoken briefly from <hi>v.</hi> 14. of Chap. 11. of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> to the end of it: where is ſet down a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102104:15"/>ſhort Abridgment of the ſtate of the World, and the Church, after the ſeventh Trumpet begins to ſound: onely many incouragements are intermixt all along for all ſorts of faithful, ſuffering Chriſtians, from the promiſes and encouragements, referring to the thouſand years, enſuing the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, which promiſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements are either contained in the firſt Viſion, reſpecting the times then preſent, or paſt, to the end of the third chapter, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> then in being: or thoſe that were to come in the following Viſions from the 4th and 5th Chapters; which Viſions are contained firſt in the Seal-Propheſie, chapters 6, 7, 8, 9. and in the 11th from <hi>v.</hi> 14 to the end of that Chapter: In the 6th chapter, are the firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth and ſixth Seals con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, which laſt ſets forth the Dragons caſting down from his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of <hi>Paganiſh</hi> worſhip, to the earth: whereupon after the ſealing of the firſt 144000 in the Eaſtern parts, chap. 7. which were to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe there and be delivered from ſpiritual ruine (as chap. 9.4.) by <hi>Mahumetan</hi> impoſtures under the two firſt woe-Trumpets, chap. 9. with the decyphering the innumerable companies of all nations to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe in the Church after the ſounding of the 7th Trumpet, in thoſe peaceable times, with palms in their hands. Then in the beginning of the 8th chapter, is the opening of the 7th ſeal, out of which all the ſeven Angels with their ſeven Trumpets, proceed: and after inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion made by the Angel of the Covenant for the faithful ſufferers under the four firſt Trumpets which blew out wrath, for the moſt part upon the Weſtern Empire, till he that letted the coming of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt there, namely, the Weſtern Emperour was taken out of the way, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. By the incurſions of the Barbarous Nations, ſo making way for the man of ſin, and ſo by degrees to end that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire there: Then in the two firſt woe-Trumpets, (as we noted before) was brought on the like wrath, or rather much worſe, in bringing in that woful <hi>Mahumetan</hi> impoſture by the Saracens and Turks (in chap. 9.) upon the Eaſtern Empire (as before upon the Weſtern) both for their former cruel Perſecutions of the Saints, and their Antichriſtian Idolatries and Wickedneſs, as in the two laſt verſes of that ninth Chapter is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſet down. That they that eſcaped thoſe Plagues (ſaving the green graſs and trees, v. 4. of chap. 9. before ſealed, ch. 7.) repented not of the Works of their hands, that they ſhould not worſhip Devils and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols of Gold and Silver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor repented of their Murthers, and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, and Fornications, and Thefts, but to be deſtroyed at the ſeventh Trumpet, as they had deſtroyed the Earth, Chap. 11.18.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:15"/>
               <p>And after thoſe Antichriſtian Abominations had been ſo long advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Weſt under the Man of Sin, and his Ten Crowned Horns, in the time of divers Trumpets, but eſpecially the two firſt ſaid Wo-Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, under that two-fold Beaſt, by new-coined Paganiſm and Idolatry, under a ſeeming Chriſtian diſguiſe; The Dragon after his former caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to the Earth under the ſixth Seal (having given his Power, and Seat, and great Authority to the ſaid two-fold Beaſt; there are ſeven An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, having ſeven Golden Vials filled with the Wrath of Almighty God, prepared to pour them out to the ſaid Beaſts deſtruction, under the ſecond Wo-Trumpet, and beginning of the 3<hi>d</hi> Chap. 15, &amp; 16. whereupon the Kingdoms of the World become the Kingdoms of our Lord and of his Chriſt, Chap. 11.16. and Chap. 20.</p>
               <p>As may more fully appear in the fore-named Abridgment on <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and in the Letter of <hi>May</hi> 20. 1664, in the <hi>Forerunner,</hi> to which the Reader may be referred; and in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, pag. 27, 28, 29, 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what we read to be recorded of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire in <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions, is ſometimes ſet down more generally, and ſometimes more particularly, as ſeemed good to the Spirit of God to make them known to him for the benefit of his Church then, and for the better and more orderly application of what was there more darkly delivered to <hi>Daniel,</hi> to what our Lord Jeſus Chriſt hath more fully (though myſtically) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to St. <hi>John</hi> his beloved Diſciple, for his Chriſtian Church to the end of the ſaid Empire, we ſhall (by Gods gracious aſſiſtance) endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to proceed in the enſuing order.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, To ſet down what <hi>Daniel</hi> ſets forth of the beginning and riſe of that Empire.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, Of the Time and Continuance of it.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, Of the general temper, quality or nature of it.</item>
                  <item>Fourthly, Of the ſeveral States and Parts of it.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly, Of the Extent and Largeneſs of it.</item>
                  <item>Sixtly, Of the End, Ruine and Deſtruction of it.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Referring thereunto the ſeveral parts of the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> more fully explaining each particular accordingly; and ſo proceed to ſome general Obſervations and Improvements, as Gods Spirit and Word ſhall direct.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, to conſider what <hi>Daniel</hi> ſets down of the beginning and riſe of that <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; and that is done remarkably, when he comes in Chap. 11. to ſet down how by degrees it began to ariſe upon
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102104:16"/>the decay of the Greek Empire, when the two Heads of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria</hi> had long battered each other, then <hi>Rome</hi> had advantage firſt to ſhew her ſelf in anothers Right, whom as her Pupil ſhe had taken the defence of, namely, of <hi>Ptolomeus Epiphanes,</hi> the Son of <hi>Ptolomy Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopator,</hi> againſt <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Great, when his Father had left him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Child of four years old, as the Stories applied to the 13 and 17 verſes in the Abridgment, makes to appear; and therefore afterwards the <hi>Romans</hi> in v. 18. are called the Prince, and act afterwards againſt <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Great, [on their own behalf;] and to take away thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches he had caſt upon them, <hi>Vide Abridgment,</hi> v. 18. But in v. 30. the Ships of <hi>Chittim,</hi> that is, the <hi>Romans</hi> Navy, as was propheſied by <hi>Balaam, Numb</hi> 24.24. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me againſt <hi>Antiochus the Vile,</hi> by the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance whereof before <hi>Alexandria,</hi> he was forced away; which was the ancient mark for the Jews to know their laſt Oppreſſor was at hand, under the Title of the Ships of <hi>Chittim;</hi> ſo conquering that Adverſary at preſent, <hi>vide Abridgment.</hi> But after <hi>Antiochus</hi> the Vile had perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his outragious wickedneſs againſt the Jews, by reaſon of tranſgreſſions, chap. 8.23. until <hi>Javans</hi> rage ended, as in the latter end of v. 35.</p>
               <p>At the 36 ver. the Spirit of God entitles the <hi>Romans,</hi> of whom he there ſpeaks, and deſcribes them by <hi>[the King;]</hi> Not now with limitation (as before) to North or South, or any other Quarter, but abſolutely <hi>[The King]</hi> to whom belonged the ſaid Ships of <hi>Chittim</hi> before, <hi>v.</hi> 30. Now having obtained the Soveraignty which was to continue until the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God againſt the Jews was ended, ver. 36. Chap. 9.27. So that now he began to exalt himſelf above every god, as he did eminently till Chriſt was born; and then ſpake marvellous things againſt the God of gods, by his Authority blaſpheming, rejecting, killing the Son of God; the Stories whereof are contained in the Goſpels, and that time thoſe things were acted, and before the <hi>Revelation</hi> was given; yet the Spirit of God leads <hi>Daniel</hi> by ſteps to ſet forth in ſuch manner the riſe, and ſuch proceedings of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, till then, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, For the time of the enduring and continuance of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhews, chap. 9. laſt; That the Ships of <hi>Chittim</hi> being (as was obſerved, chap. 11.30.) that laſt Oppreſſor of the Jews, (as <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.24.) that ſhould afflict <hi>Aſhur,</hi> and ſhould afflict <hi>Eber,</hi> and that he alſo ſhould periſh for ever, ſo that no Oppreſſor of <hi>Eber</hi> ſhould remain after him) ſets forth his time in theſe words, holding out the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Deſolation of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Jewiſh diſperſion therewith, under the <hi>Roman</hi> Tyranny and Cruelty, <hi>[for the over ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of abominations, he ſhall make it deſolate,]</hi> (after he had ſpoken ſuch marvellous things againſt the God of gods) when in the midſt of the
<pb facs="tcp:102104:16"/>laſt week of years Chriſt dying, by his Authority ſhou'd cauſe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and Oblation to ceaſe [<hi>Jure &amp; intentionaliter,</hi> by Right, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionally] in regard of Gods inſtitution thereof (though not <hi>efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> effectually;) But then it follows, how long ſuch deſolation ſhould continue, even after his efficatious cauſingof Sacrifice and Oblation to ceaſe, (as in the Abridgment) even until the conſummation (ſaith he) and that determined ſhall be poured upon the Deſolate, by that laſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, to periſh for ever: Or by ſuch as were to bring on his perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Fifth and Sixth Trumpets, <hi>viz.</hi> The Saracens and Turks, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 9. chap. namely, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40, 41. The Saracens by puſhing at his Borders about the times of the Holy Wars (ſo called) and the Turk after them over flowing a great part of his Dominions, by his mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes help to bring him down, which is called by our Saviour the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the times of the Gentiles, whilſt (from <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) the Jews ſhould fall by the edg of the Sword, and be led away cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into all Nations, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be trodden down of the Gentiles, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.24. that is, to the end of the dayes, wherein (ſaith <hi>Daniel</hi> likewiſe) Antichriſts (the wicked little Horns) time, (as chap. 7.) wherein he ſhall have accompliſhed to have ſcattered the power of the holy people, at the end of his time, times, and the dividing of a time, being the Clayie feet of the Iron legs, chap. 12.6. and chap. 7.25. and till <hi>Michael</hi> ſtand up for the deliverance of <hi>Daniels</hi> people at that ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, chap. 12 1. And again, when from Gods eminent making of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Sacrifice and Oblation laſt, to ceaſe openly (as is probable) was in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate Emperors dayes, there ſhould from thence be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled 1290 dayes of years (even about theſe times) when the Civil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Spiritual Reſurrection of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould begin, and to 1335 dayes of years or forty five years more, it ſhould be perfected; and when <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhould ſtand up in his Lot with the Fathers, chap. 12.11, 12, 13. which continuance contains the times of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, from the beginning of the opening of the firſt Seal, when the Goſpel of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt began to be publiſhed through the whole World, and ſo all along through the ſeries of the Book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> wherein are all things contained, reſpecting the Civil State, and the Affairs of Gods Church from thence, during the time of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchie, which ſhould be accompliſhed (as was foreſhewed) until the King of Kings with his Armies in white, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould ſlaughter the Enemies, and (as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38, &amp; 39 chapters) delivering all his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſhould ſet up his own, and his Saints Kingdom, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. But in the mean time, many by tryals and ſufferings under the <hi>Roman</hi> Tyrannous yoke, ſhould be purified, and made white, chap. 12.10. having waſhed
<pb facs="tcp:102104:17"/>their Robes in the blood of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14. as alſo thoſe undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lamb-followers redeemed from among men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.4. which had his Fathers Name written on their foreheads, be redeemed alſo from the Earth, ver. 3, 4. So that the conſummation, and that determined to be p ured upon the deſolate,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Ire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ic.</hi> pag. 27, 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. contained all the time of the ſix firſt Seals, after <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtruction, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. and the ſix firſt Trumpets proceeding out of the ſixth Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.9. with the ſeven Vials under the ſixth Trumpet; or, which is the ſame time, the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Ten Perſecutions, till <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtantine</hi>'s time, with the <hi>Arrian</hi> Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions afterwards, until Antichriſts forty two months were fulfilled, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Womans Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>derneſs condition, a time, times, and half a time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. and the Contemporarie two Witneſſes propheſying in ſackcloth 1260 dayes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and from thence through the ſeven Vials at the end of the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. even to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, For the general temper and quality of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and the actings thereof ſuitable to its nature. Firſt, the nature of it is deſcribed in the great Image, to be of Iron, ſtrong and durable, to the feet and toes, wherewith a weakneſs of Myrie Clay was mixed in the Popes time, chap. 2. where (ver. 40.) the uſe of it is expreſſed, namely, that it ſhould break and bruiſe all the other in pieces.</p>
               <p>Again, chap. 7. whereas the three preceding Kingdoms are ſet forth by ſeveral Beaſts; firſt, the <hi>Caldean</hi> by its Lyon-like ſtrength, and by its proud high-ſoaring Eagles wings, before they were pluckt, and it made to ſtand on the feet as a man, v. 4. 2dly, The <hi>Perſian</hi> by a ravenous devouring Bear, with three ribs in the mouth, of <hi>Babylon, Media</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> ver. 5. 3dly, The <hi>Grecian</hi> by a Leopard, ſwift to ſnatch the prey; with four wings upon the back, and four heads, under which it ſhould afterwards rule, v. 6. But the 4th, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw in the night Viſions, a Monſtrous, Myſterious Beaſt, divers from all others; it was exceeding dreadful, terrible and ſtrong, and it had great Iron teeth, and devoured, and brake in pieces, and ſtamped the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue in pieces with the feet; wherein is compriſed the ſeven Heads of Government, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. with the Nayles of Braſs (the Senate) deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Fourth Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. all of them before the 8th, which was alſo of the 7th, and adjoineth that to them, as the feet, wherewith it at laſt ſtamped, and that together with the ten Horns, as the toes of the feet, whereby the Body is enabled to walk upright, ſaying in the end of the 7th v. And it had ten Horns, wherewith to puſh and ſubdue, and vvherein the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ength and power of its ſo doing did conſiſt; by which ten Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, ſeem not onely to be underſtood the ten crowned Kings that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102104:17"/>gave their power to the beaſt, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. but all ſuch tens wherein the <hi>Roman</hi> Power before conſiſted, as that <hi>Decem-virate,</hi> till the Twelve Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of their Laws were compoſed, the <hi>Decuriones,</hi> or Commanders of Tens, ten of which were put under the <hi>Roman</hi> Centurions, conſiſting of Ten times ten, and ſo of all greater numbers of Ten; and the Ten Provinces, before they were crowned Horns, and all <hi>Roman</hi> Power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the number of Ten, as in their ſtories is obſervable; of which it might be ſaid it had ten Horns. And it is obſervable, that <hi>Daniel</hi> ch. 2. 34, 41, 42, 43. deſcribes it, that the feet and toes thereof were mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Myrie Clay; which are the ſame with the ten Horns crowned in the Popes time, which had much weakneſs in them, and could not mix themſelves with the Seed of men; and they were ſo diſtinguiſhed from ſuch former ſtrength of the <hi>Romans,</hi> in that they were the laſt and the loweſt part in that Image to help (as was ſaid) for a time to make that Beaſt ſtand, or go on the feet, as the ten toes thereof, though mixed with Myrie Clay; and with theſe ten Horns or Toes, the little Horn which <hi>Daniel</hi> obſerved, came up amongſt them, or behind them, at one hour with them, as is explained <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. before whom there were three of the firſt Horns plucked up by the Roots, <hi>viz.</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> the <hi>Lumbards, Franks</hi> and <hi>Greeks;</hi> which Horn had eyes as a man, and a mouth ſpeaking great things; and that, ſaith <hi>Dan.</hi> chap. 7.25. againſt the Moſt High <hi>[by blaſphemies and wicked errors]</hi> and did think to change times and laws, and have the Saints given into his hands for a time, times, and the dividing of a time, or 42 months, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.6.</p>
               <p>Again in chap. 11. v. 36. <hi>Daniel</hi> deſcribes the proud Uſurpation, Blaſphemy and Tyranny of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, before Antichriſts time, and in his time, v. 37, 38, 39. he more eſpecially ſpeaks of his neglect of the true God, and his Inſtitution of Marriage, with all his errors in both reſpects, with his Pride, Idolatry, and falſe Worſhip, his wicked Uſurpations and Perſecutions, to advance his Creatures to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor his Breaden God, and do all for the advancing of his Worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and outward glory.</p>
               <p>Now in all theſe deſcriptions of the nature and qualities of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Monarchy, both from its riſe under the firſt Heads of Government by Kings, Conſuls, Tribunes, Decemvires, Dictators, <hi>Coeſars,</hi> five of which were paſſed in a few years; but even in them, and more in the two longeſt and laſt, have thoſe qualities deciphered in general, been very obſervable in their ſtrength, pride, blaſphemy, tyranny, idolatry, perſecution of <hi>Jews</hi> and Gentiles, and actings againſt the God of gods, as was hinted before in the <hi>Abridgment,</hi> but might largely out of the Stories of them, be ſet forth both from Heathen and Chriſtian Writers,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102104:18"/>before and ſince the <hi>Revelation</hi> was given by Jeſus Chriſt; but chiefly, ſince their doings have been recorded by the Evangeliſts in the Goſpels, and the Apoſtles in all the New-Teſtament; and above all, in Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Propheſies concerning the Affairs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy in the greateſt part of the Book of <hi>Revelations;</hi> for after the <hi>Romans</hi> were at their height under the Emperors, beſides their Tyranny over the known parts of the world; what perſecutions were raiſed by their Emperors againſt the primative Chriſtians, executed in ſuch Savage and inexpreſſible tortures all along in the primative times under moſt of the Seals, thoſe ages that ſuffered under them, have had ſad experience, which hath ſince under the Trumpets procured that wrath of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Empire both Eaſt and Weſt, that hath long ſince extinguiſhed the Power and Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours. And though ſince that <hi>Roman</hi> Antichriſt the Pope, of the ſame fierce, tyrannous and wicked nature and qualities, by the Dragons Aſſignment did wind him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſubtilly into their place, under a Chriſtian Viſor to ſet up his new formed Idolatry; yet he hath ſhewed himſelf their Succeſſor in his kind, in their wicked and abominable proceedings, as well as in place, as the large Comments witneſs, that have been made by his perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as the Writers of them teſtifie, according to what our Saviour fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13, &amp; 17. of the Popes making War with the Saints, and the Whores drunkenneſs with their blood, and making the World, and the Kings of the Earth drunk with the Cup of her ſpiritual Fornications, and bewitching them with her Sorceries in ſuch an evident manner, as that the Myſteries of her iniquities are now in large Characters ſo legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the whole Chriſtian World, and have been many ages, that as the Prophets Viſions of old, who ſo runneth may read them; and that in the long continued ſeries of many hundreds of years paſt, and which makes the horrid wickedneſs of theſe Antichriſtians ſo much the more abominable, that under the Name of Chriſt, they have all along fought againſt Chriſt, while ſuch horrid wickedneſſes of all ſorts have been var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed over with pretences of Chriſtianity, Piety and Charity, whereby they are the more ripened for heavier Judgments than fell upon their Heatheniſh Predeceſſors, which could not be guilty of their hypocriſie and fighting againſt God and Chriſt in his Saints, in ſo abundant clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of light, againſt all conviction of Conſcience; ſo that whether we conſider the nature and quality of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy in general, or their ſeveral Heads, paſſing in order to Antichriſts (the Popes) forty two Months, and weigh their actings and proceedings accordingly, (as in large Volumes might be made evident) the deſcriptions of them are ſo natural, which <hi>Daniel</hi> by the Spirit of Propheſie ſet down afore-hand
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102104:18"/>of them, as we ſay, <hi>[non ovum ovo ſimilius]</hi> nothing is more like then what their doings have proved them to be, as all the Orders of times under the former Heads of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, from the firſt Seals, to the end of the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11.
<note place="margin">See <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 27, 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> both have for the time by-paſt, and will for what remains, according to Gods Word, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly make evident through all thoſe Ages.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Paſs we then to the Fourth Head conſiderable in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Monarchy, and that is the ſeveral Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and Parts of it: Many of theſe indeed are not ſo evident from <hi>Daniel,</hi> being (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) ſet down by him but in <hi>imagine confuſa,</hi> and not <hi>ſecundum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries rerum gerendarum,</hi> as they are by Chriſt in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> yet the greateſt things to be fulfilled after the <hi>Revelations</hi> took place, which did concern the Chriſtian churches ſince, and preſent, under this conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the ſtates and parts of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, are ſince the diviſion thereof into the Eaſt and Weſt, whereof we have theſe diſtinct informations, that the Pope ariſing with the ten Kings at one hour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. are particularly decyphered <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.8. where the wicked little Horn is obſerved by <hi>Daniel</hi> to ariſe among the other ten; before whom three of the firſt horns (as was ſhewed) were pluckt up by the roots; in which Horn were eyes like a man, and a mouth ſpeaking great things; and v. 25. againſt the Moſt High; and ſhall wear out the Saints of the Moſt High, and ſhall think to change Times and Laws, and that the Saints ſhould be given into his hand for a time, times, and the dividing of a time, by Chriſt plainly expounded, which the fulfilling of it hath plainly mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted to have been acted in the Weſtern Empire many hundred years paſt, of which chap. 2. of the feet and toes of the Image, mixed with Myrie clay, <hi>Daniel</hi> likewiſe ſpeaketh, and of the Pope, and his ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Power of the holy people a time, times, and the dividing of a time, ch. 12.6. and what we obſerved to be ſpoken of him, chap. 11.37, 38, 39. the like we have of the other part and ſtate of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire in the Eaſt, when God raiſed thoſe two Wo-Trumpets of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetans,</hi> the <hi>Saracens</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> that by degrees firſt in the time of the holy War (ſo called) ſo puſhed in the Eaſtern Empire; and ſince the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Wo Trumpet by the Turks, hath ſo utterly caſt it down, that nothing remains of it to the laſt Head, now onely confin'd to the Weſt, and theſe Parts and States of it are manifeſtly explain'd in <hi>Rev.</hi> 9 and <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. and 17. chap. and many other places.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, It remains that we obſerve what <hi>Daniel</hi> informs us of the extent and largeneſs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, which (as he obſerved) had the ſtrength of Iron to beat in pieces all other Metals, chap. 2. and that of all the Beaſts it was moſt dreadful, terrible and ſtrange, chap. 7.7.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102104:19"/>and had teeth of Iron, and nails of Braſs, to devour the whole earth, and tear it down, and break it in pieces; ſo it hath appeared in actions accordingly, as in part was ſhewed in the <hi>Abridgment,</hi> and Stories may at large manifeſt, till it grew to its height in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his time, when he Decreed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, That all the world ſhould be taxed by his Authority, that is, ſo far as his power extended, and as far, in a manner, as we read the Apoſtles went their circuits in publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel to Jews or Gentiles. And as the former Monarchies ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing thoſe they ſucceeded, entred upon their Dominions, and joined them to their own, as the <hi>Perſian</hi> Bear had the three Ribs of <hi>Babylon, Media</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi> in his mouth; ſo the <hi>Grecian</hi> much of the <hi>Perſian,</hi> together with its own; though many Limbs and Parts remained of them after their greateſt breakings, as <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo ſpeaketh, their Lives were prolonged for a time and ſeaſon, chap. 17.12. So when the <hi>Roman,</hi> of all others the ſtrongeſt, terribleſt and fierceſt, came upon the Stage to act its part, beſides its own nature ſo rapacious and cruel, it had advantage after all, to make uſe of all the broken parts of the former Three, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove any before it; and therefore ſo proudly and cruelly triumphed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their ruinous ſtates on all parts, on Eaſt, and South, and North, and after, and above all, extended its Dominions very far in the Weſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, even <hi>ad toto diviſos Orbe Britannos,</hi> to theſe furtheſt known <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Iſlands, and in thoſe known parts of the World of <hi>Afia, Africa</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> was the ſpreading of the Goſpel by the Apoſtles, in ſo many Countreys mentioned in their Writings, whoſe boundary ſhewed them to be the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (in a manner) and the encouraging alſo after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the profeſſion thereof in Eaſt and Weſt, by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, when he threw down Idolatry, and ſet up, and encouraged Chriſtianity in all the Empire. And this alſo is further manifeſt by what hath been ſince taken away by the Saracens and Turks after his time, from thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Dominions; beſides the conſiderations of thoſe many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts the <hi>Romans</hi> obtained, till they came to the height, about our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours life-time, (as in the <hi>Abridgment</hi> in part is ſet down) whence it is manifeſt upon all the ſaid conſiderations, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy was of the largeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tent of all the other, and therefore by that Emperors command, the whole World was ſaid to be taxed. The <hi>Roman</hi> Empire for its largeneſs then containing (in ſome ſort) the known habitable World, or which none could withſtand; which <hi>Daniels</hi> former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions do eminently foreſhew, and even of the Pope, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. it was ſaid the World wondered after the Beaſt, and who is able to make war with him? But when the Dragon himſelf ſate in that ſeat, with his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Heads, and ten Horns of Paganiſh Perſecutions, with ſuch ample
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102104:19"/>Dominions before the Popes time. How much more might it have been ſaid, The whole world wondred after the Dragon, and who was able to make war with him? had not Chriſt himſelf in the firſt Seal, underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that encounter, and ſet him his line, how far he ſhould go, and his limits of time under the ſixth Seal, when his term ſhould end, by caſting him from his Heaven of Paganiſh Worſhip, to the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, And ſo we proceed to the laſt ſtep, or period of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel of <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie, and the Book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> as reſpecting what they ſay jointly of the end, ruine and deſtruction of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy; and firſt for the ruine of the Beaſt, chap. 7.9. the Ancient of Dayes is ſaid to have the Judgment ſet, and that with a fiery Throne, with Wheels of burning fire; and to that end a ſtream of fire iſſued and came forth from before him, and for the execution of the Judgment thoſe thouſands miniſtred unto him, and ten thouſand times ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſtood before him; and the Books were opened, and the firſt part of the execution, and the ſpecial occaſions thereof, ſeems to be upon the provocation of the Beaſt, ver. 11. becauſe of the great words which the Horn ſpake; which execution is done firſt upon the Beaſt, to ſlay him, and deſtroy his body with the burning flame; and ſo again ver. 26. the end of the Judgment is declared to be, to take away the Dominion of the Beaſt, to conſume and deſtroy it unto the end. And <hi>Daniel</hi> then further ſaw, ver. 13. one coming in the clouds of Heaven like the Son of man, the ſame which <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. is ſaid to come with clouds, and every eye ſhall ſee him, and they alſo that pierced him; with <hi>[Even ſo, Am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>]</hi> added; ſhewing then, that promiſed Mercy is then to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled to the Jews, <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10. That they ſhall then mourn with peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent contrition, though many others with woful lamentation at that time; and unto this was the glorious deſcription of the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega;</hi> the ſaid Son of Man ſet before him, who at the finiſhing of the things of this Book, ſaith, he comes quickly; and of this coming of Chriſt, ſpeaks the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>When the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels in flaming fire, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vengeance on them that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power;</hi> when on the other hand, <hi>he ſhall be admired of his Saints, and glorified in all them that believe:</hi> And in the next Chapter, ver. 3, 4. he deſcribes the man of ſin, againſt whoſe wickedneſs, the Apoſtle ſhews (with <hi>Daniel</hi>) he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ially be revealed; whom (ſaith he) ver. 5. <hi>the Lord ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the appearance of his coming;</hi> and in like manner when that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102104:20"/>King of Kings, with his Armies in the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. cometh againſt the Beaſt and his Armies; and then takes the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet, they are both ſaid to be caſt alive into a Lake of fire and brimſtone, thereby deſcribing the Helliſh deſtruction that then will fall upon that <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy for ever. Now as the <hi>Roman</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, the ſtrongeſt and fierceſt, and of much the longeſt continuance, hath been the moſt wicked, having attempted by abominable Idolatries, Bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phemies, and unheard of cruelties in their perſecutions, ſo highly againſt Chriſt and his Saints, in thoſe ten moſt barbarous Perſecutions, notwith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anding all the light tendered in their Dominions by the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt himſelf, and his Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les, whom they likewiſe had rejected, pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecuted and killed, for the moſt part; and ſo all along the prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tive times bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed their power, to extinguiſh the Chriſtian Religion, until God raiſed up <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, to put a period to their Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh proceedings, in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>readful manner that the wrath of the Lamb, as it is ſaid, was executed upon them, that is, for the terribleneſs of it reſembled to the day of Judgment, as is largely ſet down under the ſixth Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. latter end: But when upon the taking away of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of thoſe Heatheniſh Perſecutors, the afterwards Apoſtatical Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did become Antichriſtian, though the extent of their power hath been leſſened, yet their wickedneſs, ſo far as they then could reach, hath been many wayes greater, and more notorious, and that for a longer time after their former owning of the Truth, and again revolt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it, and even perverting it to their own and others ruine in ſuch a myſterious, contrived Helliſh Apoſtaſie, by ſuch Artifice of bloody cruelty and wickedneſs, ſo monſtrouſly executed above their Paganiſh Predeceſſors, ſo many hundred years together, by their long holding out the Cup of Spiritual Abominations by <hi>Myſtery Babylon</hi> the great, the Mother of Harlots and Abominations of the Earth, who by how much more ſhe hath taken pleaſure in her wickedneſs, ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he more torment ſhall be given her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.7. But beſides the laſt fiery deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole Monarchy, by the fiery ſtreams, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. there is a further dreadful deſcription of that Wrath and Judgment, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. at the time when <hi>Michael</hi> ſhall ſtand up for <hi>Daniels</hi> people, and when his people ſhall be delivered, which ſhall be ſuch a time of trouble as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was ſince there was a Nation; whereof <hi>Babylon</hi> muſt have her por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for both <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> that is, <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> whoſe deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was revealed to <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> chap. 38, 39. to precede the ſaid deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance promiſed, chap. 37. and building of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> chap. 40. to the end of the Book; whoſe Name is <hi>Jehovah Shammah,</hi> the Lord is there, appears to be the ſame with that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> coming down out of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102104:20"/>Heaven from God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. when the Tabernacle of God will be with men, when the Lamb will be the light of that City, ver. 23. after the <hi>Armageddon</hi> battel was ended, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, to the end; and that the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> are meant in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38, 39. may appear by many paſſages, ſome whereof we may point out by the way, as chap. 38.8. it is ſaid of <hi>Gog,</hi> That he ſhall come into the Land that is brought back from the Sword, and gathered out of many people, againſt the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which have been always vvaſt for ſo very long a time; and yet (he ſaith) being brought out of the Nations, they ſhall dwell, ſafely all of them. Again it is ſald, He ſhall come out, and many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with him, out of the North parts, and that in the latter days, ver. 16. with many other notes decyphering the <hi>Turk,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo did, chap. 11.44, 45. And for <hi>Magog</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> (ſaith he alſo) chap. 39.6. <hi>I will ſend a fire on Magog, and amongſt them that dwell careleſly in the Iſles,</hi> (as the <hi>Jews</hi> reckoned ſuch remote parts under the Name of the Iſles) and then he adds, <hi>They ſhall know that I am the Lord;</hi> namely, to their coſt at the Beaſts deſtruction, more fully ſet forth in the New-T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as was ſhewed before; and then in the next Chapter the Prophet adjoins the glorious City, whoſe Name ſhould be <hi>Jehovah Shammah,</hi> the Lord is there; and to this likewiſe agrees that Propheſie of <hi>Joel,</hi> chap. 3.12. when God vvill bring again the captivity of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and as follows, vvith all <hi>Iſrael;</hi> when he vvil ſo dreadfully viſit the World, as <hi>Joel</hi> 2.30, 31, 32. <hi>Joel</hi> 3.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in a great part of that chapter ſetting forth the gathering to the <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddon</hi> Battel; and Gods Judgments on them there, may be evident, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 16, 18, &amp; 19. chapters; vvhereupon the happy eſtate of the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Church (with others) is deſcribed, when the Lord ſhall dwel among them. Conſider theſe particulars in the laſt of <hi>Joel,</hi> and as they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained in the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; ſo alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15, 16, 17. Now that the time of the accompliſhment of that terrible laſt deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy doth near approach, beſides many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conjectures of many Learned Authors, as Mr. <hi>Brightmans,</hi> Dr. <hi>Alſteds,</hi> Mr. <hi>Medes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Parkers,</hi> and other accounts, which upon ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry grounds they drew to ſome nearneſs to what we ſhall briefly ſet down, as Dr. <hi>Homes</hi> in his <hi>Dawning of the Day-Star,</hi> Lib. 7. judiciouſly explaineth them, and as daily more and more by Gods Mercy towards his people, is like to be diſcovered of the clearneſs of ſuch myſteries concerning theſe laſt days. We ſhall, I ſay, onely add four concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring computations of Scripture, of the time which may bring the laſt deſtruction of Antichriſt, at the appearing of Chriſts coming, (as 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8.) to be nearer then their former accounts riſe unto.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:102104:21"/>
               <p>Not here to inſiſt upon ſome late Authors computations, vvho have brought the accounts of the laſt things nearer than the former, <hi>viz.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Appearance of Chriſt to be at, or about <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1700; whoſe grounds, becauſe I know not what they are, I ſhall here ſay no more of them. But I find four computations of holy Scriptures tending to ſuch purpoſes: Firſt, two of the Old-Teſtament, reſpecting the end of the <hi>Jews</hi> Bondage, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. ch. Secondly, two in the New-Teſtament, for the uſe of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians, holding out firſt the ruine both general and compleat, of the great Myſtical Oppreſſor of the two Sack-cloath Propheſiers, and the contemporary Saints with them, till then, namely, of the Pope, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and 13, &amp; 16. The other the ruine of the Great Tyrant over the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtians</hi> too, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. namely, the <hi>Turk,</hi> though not over them alone, but over the outward man of the 444000 ſealed ones, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. in the Eaſt, who after his day, hour, month and year, or 396 years, to deſtroy the third part of men, muſt come to his end, when none ſhall help him, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.45. (very probably) at, or about the ſame time. Which two Ends, namely, the ruine of Chriſts Enemies, and the deliverance of his people, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1.
<note place="margin">See plain Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cov. after the Parallels.</note> are the joint work of ſuch Chriſts perſonal Appearance (then) as afterward by the goodneſs of God may more fully appear.</p>
               <p>And though the concurrence of the ſaid four Periods, ſeemed ſtrange at my firſt apprehenſions of them; yet upon ſerious conſideration ſince, I have found them exceeding probably to point out unto us the meaning of Gods Spirit therein, (in a latitude at leaſt;) and let all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Chriſtians beware of ſlighting of them. It had been a very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable thing, if four ſuch Numbers had ſo concurred onely at one period, had the holy Ghoſt done no more; ſince it was his own Divine Work ſo to ſet them down, and eſpecially, having ſuch diſtinct <hi>Epo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaes,</hi> or beginnings, many hundred of years diſtant; but when he hath expreſly, and remarkably too, cauſed the Context to ſpeak much to the like purpoſe, we are to take notice more groundedly of ſuch hints of Gods own giving, or rather Divine Foundations of ſuch kind of Truths reſpecting his own times and ſeaſons; which as they are always both for diſcovery and execution too, in his own power; yet in what degrees he pleaſes, he uſeth to make them known unto his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in ſeveral ages, as in his wiſe counſel is beſt and moſt ſeaſonable (many times) to ſtir up his ſervants to Chriſtian watchfulneſs and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. I ſhall therefore endeavour as briefly and clearly as God ſhall enable me, to ſet them down for the uſe of faithful Chriſtians, and ſo leave them, onely adding my prayers for them, firſt to beware of that ſlight overlooking of ſuch Gods Warnings, as I find too many too apt to
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102104:21"/>do.
<note place="margin">See plain Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcov. after the Patal. in 9. uſe of ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines once for all in writing, to be enlarged in Diſcourſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of all ſorts.</note> Secondly, That they may really endeavour to make their due im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements of them; to which purpoſes we may (if God will) afford ſome brief hints at leaſt, by reaſon of many preſent reſtraints from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging, as judicious perſons will eaſily apprehend.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, to ſpeak ſomething more particularly concerning the 2300 days, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. in the Original Evening-mornings, which may as well, yea, better appear, (as I doubt not after is manifeſt) to be intended for ſo many natural days, whereby we are prophetically to underſtand ſo many dayes of years (as is uſual in this kind) allowing an Evening and Morning to every day, rather than to put them (as ſome ſeem to do) for half the time: And they evidently appear from divers paſſages in the Context, to have a further intention, than to be limited to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Tyranny of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> or about his time, (which before in the <hi>Abridgment</hi> we made mention of) which evil time (happily) might be typical of the long diſperſion, and miſerable bondage of both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraclites</hi> through all their whole captivity, [that is, from the time that the captivity of both took place] to wit, from <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> beginning of the ſeventy years of his Kingdoms Tyranny over that captivated people, <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3398. and through a great part of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchy, to the beginning of <hi>Daniels</hi> Weeks, <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3549. which was 80 years more; which with the former 70 of the <hi>Babylonian</hi> captivity, amount to 150 years thus reckoned; <hi>Cambyſes</hi> with the <hi>Magi,</hi> 8 years; <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis</hi> 34, <hi>Xerxes</hi> 20, <hi>Artaxer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xes Longimanus,</hi> current 20, not compleat; which with ſome other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductings of one year, makes in Chronology 80 years, from <hi>Cyrus</hi> his taking of <hi>Babylon, Ann. Mundi.</hi> 3469, to the beginning of <hi>Daniels</hi> Wecks, <hi>An.</hi> 3549. when the Decree to build <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> not the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (that being built before that time) was ſet forth, as <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.25. in the 20th year of <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus,</hi> as <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.2, 4. and 2.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unto which, if we add the 490 in <hi>Daniels</hi> Weeks, extending 34 years after Chriſts Birth [beſides the laſt half Week after his death] in both which, namely 150, and 490, are contained 640 years, where by the way, take thoſe 34 years from Chriſts aſcention, and add them to this preſent <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1666. (and according to what is obſervable from our four Scriptural Numbers, reſpecting both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi>) they reach juſt to 1700, and ſo there will be 1666 years from Chriſts aſcending, to his deſcending the ſecond time of his coming, when will be the final ruine of the Beaſt, (by the ſaid numbers, and as far as we can gueſs by the Series of <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi>) (which ſeems remarkable in the wonderful Numberers Accounts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) according as the Angel told the Diſciples when he was taken by the Clouds out of their ſight.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102104:22"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11, 12. that he ſhould ſo come again, and not onely in the clouds of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. but probably then alſo his feet may ſtand again on <hi>Mount Olivet</hi> to fulfil that Propheſie <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.4. when the great things there ſpoken of largely, may be fulfilled, and the Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> born in a day, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 66.8. <hi>Zac.</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p>Now that the whole time from the beginning of the compleat capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of all the twelve Tribes, at the carrying of the two laſt Tribes to <hi>Babylon,</hi> was the time thenceforward to be meaſured out by the 2300 years, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.14. may appear evident from the context, thus, as is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther explained in ver. 17, and 19. and conſidered with the former; and that both (firſt) for the matter or things held out in the Viſion. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, For the time of it, and that in two reſpects; 1. For continuance thereof 2300 years. 2dly, Of the determination of the period thereof, at the laſt end of the indignation the end ſhall be; and for the matter of the Viſion, that is ſet forth, ver. 14. upon a queſtion of one Saint to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, <hi>How long?</hi> concerning the daily Sacrifice, and the tranſgreſſion of deſolation, or making deſolate, (as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word denotes) to give both the Sanctuary and the Hoſt to be trodden under foot. And further, in reſpect of the time both for the continuance and period thereof (as was obſerved) there is further added, <hi>What ſhall then be done?</hi> ver. 14. Then ſhall the Sanctuary be cleanſed, (<hi>Hebr.</hi> juſtified;) as if it was ſaid, The purpoſe of all before ſet forth formerly in the Sanctuary, will then be made evident, when the myſtery of God will be finiſhed. And afterwards one in the appearance of a man (which it ſeems was Chriſt) ſpake unto the Angel <hi>Gabriel</hi> to make <hi>Daniel</hi> underſtand the Viſion, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7. to wit, when the period thereof ſhould be; which firſt he ſaith, ver. 17. it ſhall be at the time of the end; and ver. 19. he ſaith further, it ſhall be at the laſt end of the indignation, which is again ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and further explained, chap. 11.36. and alſo comparing v. 40. of that 11th chap. with chap. 12.4, 9. and with theſe three laſt Verſes, compare the laſt ver. of ch. 12. when <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhall ſtand up in his lot. And although the two Tribes, to fulfil Gods promiſe, were ſent back in part from <hi>Babylon</hi> after ſeventy years; yet never were thoſe two of <hi>Judah,</hi> or the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in any great meaſure comparatively to the whole, either any long time freed from their bondage and oppreſſions, or had free Governors, not tributary or ſubordinate unto others; and what multitudes of them remained in the 127 Provinces of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, not much above 70 years afterwards, in the time of <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> (who is probably conceived to be <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus</hi>) from whom the Decree came to build <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (as we ſhewed from <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.25.) Beſides, they wanted the Ark where God formerly manifeſted his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102104:22"/>with them, and his pleaſure to them, with many excellencies they formerly had; yet God was pleaſed to uphold that unworthy people in their low condition divers hundreds of years, until the Tyranny of three great Oppreſſors, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Perſians, Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> till his time of <hi>Shiloh</hi> his coming, when that bleſſed promiſed Seed of the Woman, that Seed of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> in whom all Nations ſhould be bleſſed; that off-ſpring of <hi>David</hi> according to the fleſh, ſhould take our narure upon him from a pure Virgin, being conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, and in all other particulars foretold and promiſed to be the Great Meſſiah, at that appointed time to come and take upon him ſo wonderfully and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the humane nature, that he might therein fulfil all righteouſneſs, make attonement for iniquity; and bring in everlaſting righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c. Dan.</hi> 9.24. And becauſe neither <hi>Mercies</hi> nor <hi>Puniſhments</hi> wrought in any ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table meaſure upon thoſe that were reduced; but rather they grew for the moſt part worſe and worſe, and did but more fill up the meaſure of their wickedneſs, by abuſing of ſuch wonderful mercies from firſt to laſt, even ſo that they, with their Rulers, againſt all light and conviction, would joyn in killing that Lord of Life that ſo wonderfully came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and lived in the World to ſave their ſouls; and therefore they have ſeemed almoſt ever ſince to have had ſo much a worſe Captivity and ſcattering throughout the World, and ſo much the more heavy wrath lying upon them, than before; and ſeem more like to be given up to a reprobate ſenſe, till the end of the Indignation, (as it is ſeveral times called, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.19. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36.) ſo that a more evident manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the drift of this Viſion to reach to the laſt end of the indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, (as will alſo be manifeſt in all the following Myſtical Numbers) and when the end ſhall be, and in the end, as Chap. 8. v. 19. laſt words. I ſay, a greater manifeſtation thereof than this, I know not hovv, vvhere, or upon what ground vve can in reaſon expect to find.</p>
               <p>The Second is, from the years revealed to <hi>Daniel</hi> for the benefit of his own people the <hi>Jews,</hi> namely, The 1290 days of years, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocha whereof ſhould be from the time the publike daylie Sacrifice was laſt and moſt effectually taken away, and the Abomination of Deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſet up, after our Saviour (<hi>Jure,</hi> by his death had put an end to it, being the Anti-type of all ſuch Sacrifice) it was again done providentially by many ſteps afterwards; and that not only at the great Deſolation by <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> but as we ſhewed in the Abridgment on <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.27. at ſeveral times afterwards, as by <hi>Adrian</hi> the Emperor, about 130 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſts birth. Again, by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, vvhen he drave the <hi>Jews</hi> from <hi>Mamre,</hi> and ſet up a Temple for Chriſtians there: But moſt remarkable in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtates time, when the wonderful hand of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102104:23"/>God about 366, or as learned Dr. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> 363. ſhewed it ſelf in cauſing the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> publike Sacrifice, eſpecially at the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to ceaſe, even until there be an awakening of the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to their Civil and Spiritual reſurrection, foreſhewed <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. unto which ſaid <hi>Epocha,</hi> if we add the 1290 years, they will reach to 1656. about which time, or ſooner, relations were made by Travellers, of their private actings, by a ſecret character, ſending to their Brethren in many parts, upon ſome ſuppoſed deſign, probably conceived to be that in <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.44, of their riſing to ſeek their Land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the effect whereof we have had many times confirmed this year, 1665. So that from their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to look towards <hi>Sion,</hi> in hearkening after the tenders of Chriſts Grace (as by late information there ſeems to be hopes of in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) whereunto, if we add again the bleſſed time of Chriſts perfecting ſuch a work about the 13 35th year after, which is 45 years more, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.11, 12. when <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Michael</hi> their Prince ſhould ſtand up for their full deliverance at the ruine of the <hi>Turk,</hi> in the end of chap. 11. So theſe and the late Authors computations agree together about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1700.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, We may add another concurrent Account of the <hi>Turks</hi> time, in <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. who is reckoned the ſecond Wo Trumpet upon the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire, whoſe hour, day, month and year, Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſums up to be 396 years, beginning ſoon after 1300, as Chronologers compute his beginning; ſo by that reckoning about 35 years from this 1665th year, his time will be out at, or about 1700.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The like reckoning may probably be made from the Popes riſe and ruine, and from the probable proceeding of the pouring out the Viols, and the killing and riſing of the Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, From the Popes riſe at one hour, with the ten crowned Horns, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. about 406, as <hi>[Excidium Antichriſti]</hi> makes to appear very probable; and accordidgly his ruine likely eminently to begin about 1666. To which purpoſe further take notice, That Pope <hi>I nocent</hi> the firſt, at 406, or ſooner, (as ſome conceive) did not only challenge Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals to be made to him from all Churches, <hi>Secundum Patrum illorum inflituta,</hi> &amp;c. upon a pretence of a Decree in the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> which afterwards proved but a falſification, as divers Authors witneſs; but being Pope, ſaith <hi>Helvic. An. Dom.</hi> 402, alſo exalted himſelf above all that is called God, manifeſt by his Excommunicating the Emperor <hi>Arcadius</hi> in the Eaſt: <hi>See Dan. Pareus in Medulla Hiſtoriae Eccleſiae <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> and the Eaſtern Churches with him. See <hi>Roſſe</hi> Hiſtory of the World, lib. 3. ch. 3.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:102104:23"/>
               <p>He alſo is ſtoried to have obtained of <hi>Honnorius</hi> Emperor of the Weſt, an Exemption of the Clergy from the Civil Juriſdiction, making them a diſtinct Body with the Pope their Head, as the two Horned Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. as in reſpect of the ten crowned Horns that aroſe with him, he was the ten Horned Beaſt alſo; beſides many other badges to diſcover him both before, and about 406, and before in many things, as Idolatry in worſhipping Images, Saints and their Reliques, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Wolfius, Cent.</hi> 4. forbidding Marriage, <hi>Simſon Hiſt. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cent.</hi> 4. in <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> Councel of <hi>Carthage. An.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Helvic.</hi>) 396. <hi>Siricius</hi> (ſaith <hi>Melanct.</hi> on <hi>Carion. Lib.</hi> 3.) forbad the married Clergy to company with their Wives, elſe to be deprived of their Offices; abuſively citing St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, <hi>They that are in the fleſh, cannot pleaſe God:</hi> About 398. With ſundry other Superſtitions and Traditions, which Hiſtories record then to be received and promoted by the Popes in thoſe times; ſhewing the Beaſt to be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen at that time, whereof many Authors give large Evidence.</p>
               <p>Secondly, From the pouring out of the Viols; the third whereof Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> conceived to be the Laws againſt the Popes Emiſſaries in Qu. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days, with other like actings elſewhere; ſince which begun that 3d, 4th and 5th; are conceived to have paſſed in almoſt 100 years; and the 6th to be begun, both by drying up the Popes <hi>Euphrates</hi> of the <hi>German</hi> Emperors Dominions by the <hi>Turk</hi> lately; and thereby ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the way for the Kings of the Eaſt, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and <hi>Jews,</hi> as is now more then probable; and ſo to the Popes utter ruine, remains the time for gathering to the Battel of the great God, to be at the end of the 6th Viol, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. which may probably be about the ſaid time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 30 or 40 years.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The riſing of the Witneſſes will precede the falling of the tenth part of the Dition of the great City, wherein will be ſlain 7000 Names of men, at the Popes eminent beginning to fall.</p>
               <p>Now with the Date of the Beaſts 42 Months, or the Womans time, times, and half a time in her wilderneſs condition, or the witneſſes 1260 years, will probably be thoſe great changes about 1666. which the Holy Ghoſt ſeems to make the ending term or number of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. the laſt ver. as <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>'s Kingdom was ſaid to be numbred when it end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 5. when Antichriſt will have probably accompliſhed to have ſcattered the power of the holy people the Saints; but then Chriſtian Churches both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> will be able to ſtand up and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their open conflicts with both their great Adverſaries the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> the Myſtical Antichriſt, until Chriſts appearing, not improbable to be about the ſame time aforeſaid, (for ſome few years difference there is in the Computations of years in Authors) concerning the laſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102104:24"/>cauſing of Sacrifice to ceaſe in <hi>Julians</hi> time (as was obſerved) and of the time of the fixth Viol, the end whereof may happily be ſooner felt of many, then known or believed, when the 7th Viol will be poured out to fulfil that terrible deſtruction, which both Old and New-Teſtament (as was ſhewed) give witneſs unto. But all circumſtances conſidered, it may ſeem very probable upon all theſe ſaid accounts ſo concurring in a joint period, That the Great and Dreadful Day of the Lord, to the wicked World, approaches nigh, before which an <hi>Elias</hi> was to be ſent to his ancient people of <hi>Iſrael, Mal.</hi> 4.5. happily already come to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> we now hear of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Upon all which conſiderations it behoves all ſorts of men wiſely to weigh in the ballance of the Sanctuary both theſe and ſuch like Scriptural Advertiſements, and all other providential ſigns of the times; otherwiſe our manifold Warnings both from the Word and Providence, will make our Judgment the more heavy, and our neglect thereof will make us the more inexcuſable; and wo be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us if we unfaithfully go about to put off the evil day far from us, when God is about to bring it ſuddenly upon us: His Judgments begin now to appear terrible in the World, and he ſeems to begin his great Earth-quake to come, when the Beaſts eminent fall is to begin. Therefore let all the Inhabitants of the World learn righteouſneſs, both righteouſneſs of Juſtification, by the right knowledg and application of the Doctrine of Faith in Jeſus Chriſt alone, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of new obedience, being led by the Spirit of Sanctification, by the Rule of the Word, in the pathes of Holineſs, Righteouſneſs and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety in their whole life and converſation, which are thoſe Garments moſt needful at ſuch times to be kept cloſe to us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15. againſt theſe times wherein the ſtorms of Gods wrath begin to ariſe upon the wicked world in theſe laſt of dayes.</p>
               <p>And ſo we have done with the ſixth and laſt Conſideration, to wit, of the utter ruine and perdition of the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, and all the broken Limbs of the other with it; whereunto the Monarchy of Chriſt is ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſucceed, in the next place to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Here onely let me add the Conſideration of the proportioned Degrees of Gods proceedings againſt three ſorts of men in three great revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of times, wherein partly he hath manifeſted, and partly he will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt moſt eminently his wonderful Grace, ſince the old Worlds drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by water, and <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrahs</hi> deſtruction by fire, ſet forth for examples to all ſucceeding ages; and yet, for ought we find, they had not the like tenders of Grace that thoſe ſince their deſtruction have had, and yet will have; Firſt, Againſt the <hi>Jews</hi> at their laſt deſolation and captivity. Secondly, Againſt Antichriſt at his utter perdition. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:102104:24"/>What his word declares ſhall be againſt that laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> at the worlds laſt deſtruction; (for theſe terms of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> are taken for the great, reſolved and implacable Enemies of Gods Church:) Firſt, The Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> were brought near to God after all the twelve Tribes deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſetling in <hi>Canaaan,</hi> enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above their Brethren, a peculiar nearneſs to God, more than any other people, a long time; having his Oracles, and Ordinances, and Meſſengers amongſt them, and many tokens of his gracious preſence with them, great things revealed to them, great things done for them, and long patience exerciſed towards them; but when they continued not onely unreformed, but obſtinate, that they ſet themſelves againſt God and his Meſſengers, in ſuch a notorious, rebellious manner, that there was no remedy, they were led Captive to <hi>Babylon;</hi> but yet with a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſe of returning again after 70 years. But afterwards, when neither Mercy nor Judgments did them good, but after all their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and tranſgreſſions, they killed the Lord of Life, and perſecuted his Meſſengers that ſought to ſave their fouls; ſuch an horrible deſolation befell them, as in all the world the like had not been heard. But 2dly, Since the <hi>Romans</hi> have rejected greater tenders of Grace, wherein both Chriſts and his Apoſtles both Preachings and Miracles, were performed, and whereby the <hi>Jews</hi> Deſolation was accompliſhed for reſiſting of Chriſt and his Goſpel, which after the wicked Example of the <hi>Jews,</hi> they have ſo rejected, deſpiſed, yea oppoſed and perſecuted both the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and all that owned it, in ſuch bloody, cruel and ſavage manner, that the juſt wrath and vengeance of Almighty God, hath almoſt all along purſued them; but eſpecially it will appear in the utter ruine of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Kingdom, at Antichriſts deſtruction, who hath of all others abuſed the greateſt, cleareſt and moſt glorious light of Goſpel-Grace, after his fore-fathers owning of it, and taking up a profeſſion thereof; yet after by his abominable Apoſtaſie, ſo wickedly to pervert ſuch precious Truth, and ſo many hundred years to proceed in ſuch abominable, helliſh practiſes of Atheiſm, Blaſphemy, Idolatry, with all varieties of VVic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, Perſecution and Bloodſhed of the Saints, his laſt utter ruine will (according to the VVord) be ſo much the more terrible, by an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate hand of Chriſt, by Fire and Sword, and otherways to make it ſo dreadful to all ſucceeding Generations, as is ſaid <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. and <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38, 39. in reference both to him and the <hi>Turk,</hi> who hath likewiſe got ſo great a ſhare in the Empire, (where the falſe Prophet <hi>Mahomet</hi> is alſo ſet up) that it will be a time of trouble, ſuch as never was ſince there was a Nation; more fully again explained of the Pope, and (happily) that falſe Prophet too, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, 11, to the end.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:25"/>
               <p>But 3dly, VVhen the Hypocriſie of the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> ſo long reſtrained by the wonderful Glory, and powerful Grace of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manifeſt, both before in the deſtruction of Antichriſt, and all along the thouſand years, not onely to all the Generations of the faithful, for the inward and outward man; but to the raiſed Saints, in ſo bleſſed and holy an Eſtate, continued that time on Earth all under that Univerſal Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt and his Saints; yet notwithſtanding all reaſons and motives to the contrary, when at laſt by Satans ſeducement upon the advantage of the numerouſneſs of thoſe hypocritical ſlaves (formerly) to the Church, they ſhall ſo Atheiſtically, after all dare to break out into open Enmity and Hoſtility (probably to free themſelves from Chriſts and his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches outward yoke) to think and attempt to compaſs the Camp of Saints from all the Quarters of the Earth, by the Conduct of the Devil, and even to beſiege (as it were) Heaven it ſelf upon Earth, the beloved City, it will be an Attempt ſo far beyond all parallel in the height of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both of Men and Devils in the world, that the Vengeance of God will no longer ſuffer it to continue, nor them to have longer time further to attempt any other Evil in it; but both at once, or near together, ſhall be deſtroyed from the face of it, and ſent thence to their own place of torments, and thereupon the diſſolution of the world to enſue: Such VViſdom, Power, Holineſs, and Goodneſs of ſuch Gods great Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in the world, the Sacred Scriptures ſeem clearly to hold out to be obſerved and improved by all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:102104:25"/>
               <head>The Parallel of the Fifth Monarchy in <hi>Daniel,</hi> further Expounded in the Book of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To which purpoſe we ſhall ſet down, <hi>Firſt,</hi> Some Obſervations tending thereunto more indirectly and remotely. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> We ſhall ſummarily and briefly adjoin the particular Branches moſt conſiderable in the Parallel between <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation. Thirdly,</hi> We ſhall add ſome <hi>Explications</hi> and <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrations</hi> of ſome moſt material things further to be conſidered therein, as God ſhall aſſiſt.</head>
               <p>WHere <hi>(Firſt)</hi> obſerve, That as the Antichriſtian Church is ſet forth by Forty two Months, according to the courſe of the Moon that rules in the dark night; So <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, chap. 2.7. He ſaw the fourth Beaſt in the Night-Viſions, wherein much myſtery of iniquity was to be obſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Again obſerve, as Chriſt (<hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15.) warns all men, That he will come as a Thief in the night: So <hi>Daniel</hi> (c. 7.13.) ſaw in the Night-Viſions, <hi>The Son of Man come in the Clouds of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As the time of the Two Sack-cloth Prophets is deſcribed by 1260 days of years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. the day being the time of light and comfort; ſo the Saints (the Children of Light) are they to whom the Son of Righteouſneſs, the true Light, gives the Kingdom to poſſeſs it for ever and ever, ver. 18. when the Beaſt and his Worſhippers ſhall be caſt into utter darkneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As Chriſt makes known to his Saints, <hi>That the Beaſt ſhall make war with them, and overcome them, and kill them temporally,</hi> Rev. 13. So <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhews, that the time would enſue, that the Beaſt ſhould be ſlain, and his Body deſtroyed, and given to the burning flame, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> As the Lambs Followers (<hi>Rev.</hi> 14.) are deſcribed to be ſuch as loved not their lives unto death: So the Kingdom that belongs to
<pb facs="tcp:102104:26"/>them, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, ſhall not be deſtroyed, v. 14. but they ſhall poſſeſs it for ever and ever, v. 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> As the Woman (the true Church) is nouriſhed in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs a time, times, and half a time, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.14. that the Beaſts tyranny and perſecution might not deſtroy her, while her limited time of ſuffering laſted; ſo the Beaſt ſpeaking great words againſt the Moſt High, and wearing out the Saints, is alſo limitted by the ſaid time, times, and dividing of a time, chap. 7.25. his great Power and abuſed Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity cannot lengthen his days.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> As in <hi>Dan.</hi> ch. 2. many chief matters are ſet down of the times, nature, order or ſtates, founder or ſetter up, continuance and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valence of Chriſts glorious Kingdom on Earth, with the unlimited ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of it; ſo beſides theſe, in chap. 7. is more remarkably deſcribed the manner of raiſing it, both remote, and more near, the Donation of the Founder thereof, with the Owner of it, namely, the Son of Man his Doputation of it to the Saints, together with power to judg and rule for him over the whole world; and in chap. 12. the particular time in order is deſcribed, of the ſecond eſtate of it, which are all that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks directly of it; only indirectly, are the continuance of the firſt eſtate of it, implyed chap. 9.24, 26, 27. deſcribing what ſhall be done towards the end of the ſeventy Weeks, when Chriſt ſhould by his own Sacrifice of himſelf, cauſe the other <hi>(jure)</hi> to ceaſe, and how he ſhould confirm the Covenant with many; and after the people of the Prince, to wit, the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſhould deſtroy the City about forty two years after: And then in general, ſets down the time of its deſolation, which our Saviour calls the fulfilling of the times of the <hi>Gentiles, Luc.</hi> 21.24. which contains the firſt Eſtate of Chriſts Kingdom. Alſo it is again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly ſpoken of under the Popes wicked actings againſt it, in the ſaid firſt ſtate of it, by the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36, 37, 38, 39. So in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> what directly belongs to Chriſts glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom upon Earth, is <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. to the end, and chap. 19, 20, 21, 22. But indirectly, there are many things revealed, and ſeen, and promiſed, which refer to the New-<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that comes down from God out of Heaven for encouragements to the faithful ſufferers in their ſucceſſive times, all along ſet forth in that Book beſides: Of which more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. <hi>Vide</hi> Paper of <hi>Dec.</hi> 7.1664. in the <hi>Forerunner, p.</hi> 36, 37, 38, 39.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As to the ſecond head briefly to be adjoined, we may both from <hi>Daniel</hi> and the Book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> jointly obſerve theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar branches moſt conſiderable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The order and different ſtates of that Kingdom diſtinguiſhed by the Kingdom of Patience, and Kingdom of Power, called aptly by
<pb facs="tcp:102104:26"/>Mr. <hi>Meds,</hi> The Kingdom of the Stone, and the Kingdom of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, grounded upon <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34, 35. The firſt is deciphered under Chriſts riding conquering and to conquer, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. through all the Seals and Trumpets, to the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, which contains the time of the firſt ſtate; the Kingdom of Patience, or the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Stone ſet forth directly in all the Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thoſe laſt named chap. 11. and chap. 19, 20, 21, 22. wherein (as was ſhewed) is contained the ſecond ſtate of Chriſts Kingdom of Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power, or the Kingdom of the Mountain filling the whole Earth. Both theſe ſtates <hi>Daniel</hi> ſets down more largely: Firſt, the firſt ſtate (though indirectly) under the actings of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire againſt the God of gods, and diſregard of his Fathers God in the Emperors and Popes time, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36, 37, 38, 39. and ſo of the actings of the Fourth Beaſt, with his wicked Horn, chap. 7. and a great part of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron Kingdom, with feet and toes of Iron and Clay, ſo long as they have been the Perſecutors and Oppreſſors of Gods true Church; and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtate of it <hi>Daniel</hi> expreſſeth, when the Kingdom was given by the <hi>Ancient of Dayes</hi> to the Son of Man, chap. 7.13, 14, to the end of that Chapter.</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, Again, for the beginning of the States of the ſaid Kingdom; The beginning of the firſt was under the firſt Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. which was when Chriſt having all power given him in Heaven and in Earth, then gave Commiſſion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. to his Diſciples and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Miniſters to preach the Goſpel to all, promiſing to be with them to the end of the World, when he ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. <hi>Time</hi> (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the Beaſt and wicked Dominion) <hi>ſhould be no more;</hi> which will be finiſhed when the Beaſt ſhall be deſtroyed; which Kingdom will be perfected upon the beginning of the following ſtate, namely, of the Kingdom of Power, or the Kingdom of the Mountain, then to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. which, as that of the Stone, was many hundred years in paſſing to this laſt ſtate: So this ſhall never paſs away, or be deſtroyed while the World continues, but ſhall at laſt be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Kingdom of Glory in Heaven for evermore, as that of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was perfected in the Kingdom of Power before. Now of the time of the beginning of the firſt, ſaith <hi>Daniel,</hi> chap. 2.44. <hi>In the dayes of thoſe Kings ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a Kingdom, &amp;c.</hi> and of the beginning of the Second, (chap. 7.) ſaith he again, v. 13, 14. <hi>I ſaw the Son of man coming with the Clouds of Heaven, and unto him was given Dominion, and Glory, and a Kingdom, that all People, Nations and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages ſhould ſerve him, &amp;c.</hi> Of which more (by Gods aſſiſtance) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:27"/>
               <p n="3">3dly, We muſt eſpecially obſerve how the firſt Seſſion of the day of Judgment begins the ſaid laſt ſtate of Chriſts Kingdom, where the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſaid to be ſe, and the Books opened, at the deſtruction of the Beaſt; and upon that account, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12. becauſe of the great words which the Horn ſpake, ver. 9, 10, 11. will be executed by Chriſt at the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. to the end, ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. And likewiſe another like Seſſion of Judgment after the thouſand years, we may again obſerve will (according as God hath appointed, and our Saviour declared) <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> perfect the ſaid Kingdom of the Mountain in glory, after the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhall be deſtroyed, after the thouſand years ſhall be ended; when alſo the Judgment will again be ſet, and the Books opened, which is proper only to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great Day (as St. <hi>Jude</hi> calls it;) and why ſhould it ſeem ſtrange that Chriſt ſhould have ſuch a great Day to judg and rule in over all creatures, as he is Mediator, whilſt the Kingdom which the <hi>Ancient of Days</hi> gave him, ſhall remain in his hand, when <hi>Antichriſt</hi> had his Day of before? And not to ſpeak of the days of Captivities of the <hi>Jews,</hi> or of 1260 years their forty years in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. St. <hi>Peter</hi> reckons Eternity under the name of a day, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. laſt; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as in the Original:) So that upon many conſiderations, Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> might well reckon all that time from Chriſts coming with clouds, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13. of which <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the laſt Seſſions end, under the title of the Day of Judgment; wherein firſt, at the deſtruction of Antichriſt, when he deſtroys the quick with viſible, temporal judgment, and rewards his Servants the Prophets, and his Saints, and all that fear his Name both ſmall and great, in their order, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 5. when likewiſe <hi>Daniel</hi> ſheweth, the Saints ſhall take the Kingdom (being then given to them) and poſſeſs it for ever (to the Worlds end) as Chriſt then will receive it of his Father, to give it to them, ver. 13. yet they ſhall rule for him, ver. 27. all that time, in all Nations under the whole Heaven.</p>
               <p n="4">4thly, In the next place the God of Heaven is ſaid to be firſt the Founder of Chriſts Kingdom in the whole of it, under both ſtates of the Stone and Mountain, of Patience and Power, chap. 2.44. <hi>In the dayes of thoſe Kings the God of Heaven ſhall ſet up a Kingdom that ſhall never be deſtroyed, &amp;c.</hi> And alſo he is ſaid to be the Doner or Giver of it to Chriſt his Son, chap. 7.9, 13, 14. So likewiſe <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. Chriſt hath not onely the <hi>Revelation</hi> given to him from God the Father, to open and make known the ſame to his Church; but the Lamb hath Riches, and Honour, and Power, and Wiſdom, and Strength, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to execute and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil all things contained therein, ver. 12, 13. which he himſelf declared
<pb facs="tcp:102104:27"/>before his aſcention, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.18, 19, 20. his Commiſſion from the Father enables him to fulfil the contents of that Book in both ſtates of that Kingdom, in order from the beginning of the firſt Seal, chap. 6. when he ſent out his Apoſtles, as before, <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. to, and in his 1000. years reign on Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10.</p>
               <p n="5">5thly, So likewiſe for the extent of his Kingdom under both States: In the firſt ſtate it is large without reſtraint, unto <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles, Greeks</hi> or <hi>Barbarians,</hi> in reſpect of the tender of it, <hi>Go preach the Goſpel to every creature,</hi> Mar. 16.15. <hi>Go preach the Goſpel to all Nations,</hi> Matt. 28.19. As <hi>Auguſtus Coeſar</hi> would have all the World taxed; ſo Chriſts riding on the white Horſe hath the ſame bounds, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. No doubt <hi>their ſound went into all the world, and their words to the end of the earth,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18. So <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.24. It ſhall never be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ſhall break in pieces all thoſe Kingdoms, and extend ſometimes very largely in the Empire, and at one time or other all over the known World.</p>
               <p>But the other ſtate of the Kingdom of the Mountain, is not onely unlimited in the tender of it, but alſo boundleſs in the extent of it over all the whole Earth, as an huge Mountain it fills the whole Earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. and ch. 7.13, 14. <hi>To the Son of Man was given Dominion, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and a Kingdom, that all People, Nations and Languages ſhould ſerve him;</hi> and his Deputies, the Saints, take the Kingdom, ver. 18. and that which was the greatneſs of the Kingdom, under the whole Heaven, v. 27. and then all Dominions ſhall ſerve and obey him. So <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. the Saints reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years, and the repreſentative Church exult aſſuredly, That they ſhall reign upon Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>The Kingdoms of the World are become the Kingdoms of our God and of his Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6thly, Again, for the nature of this Kingdom, although the firſt ſtate of it, being moſtly inviſible, and therefore in the outward aſpect for the moſt part deſpiſed, neglected, yea oppoſed by the men of the World of all ſorts, for the moſt part of the time of the Kingdom of Patience, in which ſtate, though the <hi>Devil</hi> and the wicked World have endeavoured earneſtly to deſtroy it, yet it could never be deſtroyed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. And though the Beaſt make war with the Saints, and think to wear them out, yet his time is limited to a time, times, and dividing of a time; but then the Judgment ſhall ſit and deſtroy him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25, 26. even when he ſhall have accompliſhed to ſcatter the Power of the holy people, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. for he ſhall never utterly deſtroy their Power, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.6. So <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:102104:28"/>
               <p>But in the ſecond ſtate it will not onely be an inwardly inviſible, true Church, but alſo an outwardly viſible and glorious Kingdom likewiſe, when <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall be ſo largely and unlimitedly brought into it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12, <hi>&amp;c. Dan.</hi> 7.14. Even ſuch a glory as becomes the Son of God, to have Dominion and Glory, as was ſaid; and which he willed before his death the Viſion of to his Saints, <hi>John</hi> 17.24. that they ſhould be where he was <hi>[to behold his own glory]</hi> not which he had with the Father, but that which the Father had given him, as Mediator, at the Beaſts deſtruction, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.12, 14. and accordingly <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. there is a glorious deſcription of his coming at his Kingdom; and likewiſe <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At his Firſt coming there was no form nor comelineſs ſeen by moſt in the World, either in his perſon, or outward condition, when the Son of Man had not where to lay his head, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 53.2. He was called a King in ſcorn at his death, and arrayed like a King in mockery, a crucified King, in contempt; and ſuch was his Kingdom outwardly in moſt mens eyes, in regard of his Subjects, of his Officers, of his Laws, of his Ordinances in the World, moſt of the many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years of the firſt ſtate thereof, by the varieties of Perſecutors both <hi>Paganiſh</hi> and <hi>Popiſh, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7thly, As Chriſts Kingdom in the firſt State of Patience, is outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weak and oppreſſed, therefore reſembled by a Woman in a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs condition 1260 years, or a time, times, and the dividing of a time, in wearing out, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.25. and having her power ſcattered, ch. 12.7. yet inwardly, even then, it is ſpiritual and ſtrong, to conſume and break in pieces, and ſubdue, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34. it ſmites and breaks in pieces the feet and toes of the Iron and Clay; and v. 44. it ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and break in pieces all thoſe Kingdoms; and c. 7.23. it ſhall devour the whole Earth, and tread it down, and break it in pieces: [Obſerve the expreſſions] For that which is ſpiritual, is prevalent and ſtrong, above that which is outward and temporal. Hence <hi>Zac.</hi> 4.6. when the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick had its Lamps ſupplied with Oyle from the two Olive Trees: Chriſt there declares, his Church ſhould overcome, not by Power, nor by Might, but by his Spirit Hence alſo he ſaith, That he will give Power to his Two Witneſſes; that is, prevalency to propheſie, though in ſack-cloth, 1260 dayes of years, to conſume the Beaſt, and bring him low, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. the Saints alſo overcome, having waſhed their Robes in the blood of the Lamb, by a ſpiritual, powerful Victory; hence the faithful are ſtiled <hi>Overcomers,</hi> having ſpiritual Power from God derived unto them againſt all Spiritual and Worldly Adverſaries; therefore ſaith our Saviour, <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall inherit all things,</hi> Rev. 21.7. Rev. 2.7, 11. Rev. 12.13. Rev. 15.2.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:28"/>
               <p>But the ſecond ſtate of that Kingdom is not onely ſpiritually preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, but alſo outwardly powerful, to ſubdue and deſtroy; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it had ſpiritually ſmitten the Iron Kingdom in the feet and toes, before, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34. So by it, and for it ſhall the Beaſt be ſlain, and his body deſtroyed and given to the burning flame, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, to the end. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. latter end, and 16. at the end; and after that there is given to Chriſt Dominion, and Glory, and a Kingdom, that all People, Nations and Languages ſhould ſerve him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. which is the ſame with Chriſts Reign with his Saints a thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. and ſpoken of the ſame time in the ſame order of Affairs to be accompliſhed by Chriſt for himſelf and his Church; and likewife <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. relates to the ſame time of the ſounding of the ſeventh Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, when the Kingdoms of the World will be the Kingdoms of our God and of his Chriſt, as there he is praiſed for by it the twenty four El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And then Judgment (that is, <hi>judicandi poteſtas,</hi> power of Judging) will likewiſe be given to the Saints of the Moſt High, as it is ſaid, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.22. and the Kingdom, and the Dominion, and the Greatneſs of the Kingdom ſhall be given to the People of the Saints of the Moſt High, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.26, 27. Anſwerable whereunto is that Promiſe of our Saviour in reference to that ſtate and time, as Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> in his Obſervations noted, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. That <hi>to him that overcometh, he will grant to ſit with him on his Throne, even as he before had overcome, and was ſet with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on his Throne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="explanations">
               <head>Now having ſet down thoſe previous Obſervations in general; and <hi>2dly,</hi> thoſe Several Conſiderable Particularities contained in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and all expounded in the Book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> reſpecting Chriſts Kingdom on Earth, we ſhall further by Gods aſſiſtance endeavour to proceed, and to explain and illuſtrate the moſt material things that we have but hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to briefly touched upon.</head>
               <p>VVHerein we may (firſt) obſerve how <hi>Daniel</hi> deſcribes the firſt State or Kingdom of the Stone, which is the Kingdom of Patience, wherein the Saints by Faith and Patience overcome and inherit the Promiſes, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, and ſhall inherit all things, as our Saviour further promiſeth; and here we ſhall endeavour to ſhew how this Kingdom of the Stone hath in, and from the time of Chriſts life and death been carried on accordingly both before the Beaſts time under the perſecuting Heatheniſh Dragon, and ſince the Beaſts forty two Months began; and to ſhew how the Saints have ſpiritually and powerfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed
<pb facs="tcp:102104:29"/>for above 1600 years paſt, by the word of Chriſts Teſtimony, which in ſeveral reſpects, in ſeveral times, they have been enabled by his Spirit to give witneſs and teſtimony unto; and to this purpoſe <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhews, chap. 2. when he had ſet a ſummary of <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> dream before him, in v. 33. he proceeds to the Fourth Metal, figuring the Fourth or <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, wherein were the legs of Iron, and feet and toes part of Iron, and part of Clay; and in the two next ver. he minds him of the confuſion of all thoſe Kingdoms ſet forth by the four ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Metals (though it was a long time to come) and therefore he tells him, <hi>Thou ſaweſt (until) the Stone was cut out of the Mountain without hands,</hi> which time (until) he more particularly explains, v. 44. ſaying, <hi>In the dayes of thoſe Kings ſhall the God of Heaven ſet up a Kingdom which ſhall never be deſtroyed;</hi> that is, ſaith Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> In the dayes of one of thoſe Kings, and while the broken parts of the other Kingdoms remained; ſo that they had ſome life left to them, though their Dominion was taken from them, as it hath been ſince the time of the <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdom, which hath had great Conteſts by the broken parts of ſome of the former, as <hi>Perſians, Armenians, Grecians,</hi> as Stories witneſs of their wars, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſometimes been foiled by them too, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (as might be ſhewed;) but the former Text reſpecting the time of the beginning of this Kingdom, which the God of Heaven would ſet up, is more fully explained in v. 12. and chap. 7. which hath reference to that laſt Text named, and other places of <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. where he ſhews, That the Stone ſhould at laſt, after it had long before ſmitten the feet and toes of Iron and Clay in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, that were the loweſt and laſt parts of it, it ſhould (I ſay) make thoſe (together with the Silver, and the Gold, and the Braſs, and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron) at once become as the chaff of the Summer Threſhing-floor: namely, in regard of what was ſaid in chap. 7.12. to wit, though the Dominions of all the former Kingdoms were taken away, yet their lives were prolonged for a time and ſeaſon, till the laſt great and utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Fourth Beaſt ſhould be accompliſhed, when the firſt Great Judgment was ſet, and the Books opened, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. and when Chriſt came with Clouds to receive the Kingdom which his Father, the <hi>Ancient of Dayes,</hi> gave him over all the world, ver. 13, 14. which ſhould never paſs away nor be deſtroyed, as he there fully ſhews.</p>
               <p>Now how this Firſt State of the Kingdom of the Stone began to be ſet up, as it is ſtiled ver. 23. (until the Kingdom of the Mountain took place, as verſe the 34.) by the God of Heaven, and hath all along been upheld powerfully and graciouſly by him, (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> foreſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed) is to be obſerved from the Hiſtory of the
<pb facs="tcp:102104:29"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> all along the times of the Roman Empire being Contemporaries with it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicon,</hi> on <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.27 28.</note> in reſpect both of the affairs of the State under both Seals and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, now near to the end of the ſixth Trumpet, or ſecond Wo, when the Turk muſt be deſtroyed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. <hi>ult. &amp;</hi> 12.1. And alſo in reſpect of the affairs of the Church, both true and falſe, till Antichriſt, the Pope (with the former half of him, the Turk) be likewiſe deſtroyed (as is probable) at the ſame time, or near together. To which purpoſe obſerve how this ſpiritual Kingdom of the Stone was ſet up in that manner as Chriſt-ſhewed to <hi>Zachary</hi> in a Viſion, Chap. 4. how the Oyl was ſupplied to the Candleſtick and its ſeven Lamps, and ſeven Pipes thereof, from the two Olive-Trees ſtanding by it; the uſe whereof he explains verſ. 6. <hi>Not by power, nor by might, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> which is applied to the two Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and in this manner the Spirit of the Lord was (originally as in the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) upon Chriſt himſelf, being anointed above his fellows to preach the Goſpel, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1. This anointing was derived from him unto, and fell upon the Apoſtles in an abundant meaſure, and likewiſe in their meaſure upon all ſucceeding Meſſengers of Chriſt in the primitive Times, and ſo forward in the times ſucceeding till this day; and alſo on all faithful Chriſtians in their degree all along unto the Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Apoſtacy, and from thence during the Popes forty two months, wherein thoſe anointed Ones, or as the original word ſignifies, thoſe <hi>Sons of Oyl,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the two Witneſſes propheſying in Sackcloth 1260 days of years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. have fed the Woman, the true Church, in her wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs condition, her <hi>time, times and half a time,</hi> now probably almoſt expired: all which time this Oyl hath been divinely conveyed and ſupplied to preſerve that light of Divine Truth and Grace by their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry in the Candleſtick, the true Church. And as it appears this Kingdom of the Stone was at firſt ſet up ſo divinely by the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſo ſpiritually and powerfully upheld by him, that no wicked oppoſition could either deſtroy it, or hinder it, but even his ſpiritual Power and Grace made the oppoſition of men and Devils to promote it in the faithful Chriſtians inward man: So it may further appear to be his work both to ſet it up and preſerve it by the unlikelineſs of the means whereby he hath and ſtill doth the ſame; not (as was ſaid) by power and might of the World, for that not onely hath uſually been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to help in that work, but hath (with Satans help) made ſtrong and violent oppoſition againſt it, both in the Dragons heatheniſh and Antichriſts apoſtatizing times; which hath abundantly been evident both in the time of Chriſts own Miniſtry, and in the Miniſtry of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102104:30"/>who were his (<hi>Legati a latere,</hi> or) Ambaſſadors immediately ſent from him on the Meſſage of the Goſpel, with all other mediate Meſſengers and Miniſters ſent by him from their times, and alſo in all real and true ſubjects of the Kingdom of the Stone, ever ſince to this very day.</p>
               <p>To inſtance a little in each reſpect: 1. Of their own outward mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: 2. Of the Worlds fayling to help them: and 3. Of both the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils and the wicked Worlds both malicious and violent oppoſition for the moſt part made againſt them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, As Chriſt himſelf at his coming in our fleſh was that founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-Stone elect and precious, which God ſets ſuch an <hi>[Ecce] Behold</hi> unto it, that his People ſhould take notice thereof, when he ſhould lay it in <hi>Sion, Iſa.</hi> 28.16. and witneſſed unto it by other Prophets long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his coming; yet when he came into the World every way won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, in Conception, Birth, Life, Doctrine, Miracles; yea, before, in, and after his death; yet was he not by the Great Ones, or the moſt, or wiſeſt, or learnedeſt of men either owned or received: But even then, though he was very divinely and ſpiritually wonderful; yet in regard his outward aſpect and garb appeared to the Worlds Eye mean and contemptible, the very Builders themſelves rejected that elect and precious corner-Stone, though to faithful mens eyes and Angels diſcovery, very conſpicuous and glorious: So that our Saviour toward his Death applies the Prophecie of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 118.22. unto the then Rulers, which reſpected both him and them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.42. ſaying, <hi>The Stone which the Builders rejected, is become the Head of the Corner,</hi> which was the Lords own doing, and was marvellous in the Eyes of men. And ſo it hath been with the Kingdom of the Stone all along that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Patience, as we may, by Gods aſſiſtance, ſet down after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
               <p>Now how this Stone it ſelf, in reſpect of his humane Nature, may be obſerved eminently to be cut out of the Mountain by the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, without hands, was declared alſo as a wonder before he came, by the Evangelical Prophet <hi>Iſaiah; Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a Virgin ſhall conceive, and bear a Son, and his Name ſhall be Immanuel, God with us,</hi> Iſa. 7.14. So he was conceived by the holy Ghoſt, and born of his Mother a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, without any real natural Father of his Fleſh, (though he had a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted one) appointed by God himſelf to be a very uſeful help to the Virgin Mother of the Son of God; yet how mean and low were (then) their outward conditions? what attempts were made to deſtroy that ſpiritual King, as ſoon as he came into the World? How was he driven about, to endanger him in his tender infant age, ſoon after he came
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102104:30"/>into the World? How was he expoſed and driven about whilſt a child? neglected and deſpiſed by the moſt of men; and that amongſt his own People and Kindred, in the time of his private life; where it was ſo much the more hard to do good among them, by how much men uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſregard a Prophet in his own Countrey: as he ſhewed that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb to be fulfilled by them in regard of himſelf; with many other conſiderations to this purpoſe, manifeſted in the Goſpel. But after he ſhewed himſelf in publick, in preaching the Goſpel of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, declaring how that Kingdom of God was come unto them, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Kingdom of the Stone, is eaſily there obſervable.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>But why,</hi> may ſome ſay, <hi>was the ſpiritual Kingdom of Grace cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Kingdom of the Stone?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, becauſe Chriſt had been promiſed and propheſied of long before, under the Name, (as was in part ſhewed before, and might by many places of Scripture be made further evident.) Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Some Stones, as the Adamant, are harder then the four Metals, to be bruiſed by it: hence our Saviour ſaith of himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.44. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhould fall on that Stone, ſhould be broken; but on whomſoever it ſhould fall, it would grind him to powder.</hi> And though the Doctrine of the ſaid Kingdom was ſo powerfully preached by him (as was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the very Auditors themſelves to be with authority, and not as the Scribes; although he did ſuch and ſo many Miracles as never man did; and though his life was ſo perfectly exemplary, who <hi>did all things well,</hi> (as was alſo acknowledged of him) and no evil nor guile was found in his mouth, as Gods Spirit witneſſed of him; and that he went about doing good, though ſuffering evil for it: yet it was his meat and drink ſo to do his heavenly Fathers will, and to finiſh his work: and even to ſuffer ſo as no man ever did, nor all men ever could to that end; yea, how was he ſtraightened until he had fulfilled it? and all that was but to lay that Foundation of that Kingdom of the Stone, which began to appear when he was declared by his Reſurrection from the dead, to be the Son of God, with power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.14. whereupon he was ſo owned of his Father, <hi>Thou art my Son, this day have I begotten thee,</hi> Pſal. 2.7. applied <hi>Act.</hi> 13.33. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.5. and thereupon all power being given to him (as he declared ſoon after to his Diſciples) when he gave them Commiſſion to preach the Goſpel, and wherein his Divine Power ſhould chiefly be manifeſted in the World, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>viz.</hi> in preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdom, ſaying, (upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Divine Power, verſ. 18, 19, 20.) <hi>Go preach the Goſpel to all Nations,</hi> &amp;c. which Commiſſion in ſucceeding Miniſters was to reach to the end of the World, that was to be accompliſhed at his coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102104:31"/>When God ſhall bring his Son (again) into the World, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (as the Original ſhews) when all the Angels of God ſhall worſhip him, and every knee bow to him, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. and the fame World is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. <hi>the World to come;</hi> and by our Saviour, <hi>that World at the Reſurrection,</hi> Luk. 21.35. in which <hi>interim</hi> it was to be preached to all that ſhould believe through their word, for which our Saviour prayed before his death, <hi>John</hi> 17. until that great period was come, when all the World ſhould both believe and know that God the Father had ſent him (as he there ſpeaketh) yet after all the Divine Glory ſhewed in Chriſts Birth, Doctrine, Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Life, Death and Reſurrection, ſo neglected, oppoſed, gain-ſaid, perſecuted, in all Chriſt was, did, and ſuffered, ſo accompliſhed and publiſhed in the World, the Rulers believed not on him, but hindred others that would: and though many Prophecies had been fulfilled all that time in and by Chriſt, and he had foretold many others to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled by the Worlds wicked actings and proceedings againſt him, and to be fulfilled upon them for their ſo doing, in the ruine of that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their City and Nation; yet by their infidelity and wickedneſs, they brought on the accompliſhment thereof upon themſelves: and though his Doctrine was acknowledged to be ſuch as never was taught, and his Miracles ſuch as never were wrought by any other, and nothing was found in his Life or Death that juſtly could be proved againſt him; yet all was diſregarded and rejected by the moſt of men living in his time. If it was acknowledged at one time, <hi>he did all things well;</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time he was judged <hi>a drunken and a gluttonous man, a friend of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Sinners:</hi> if one time his Doctrine ſeemed Divine and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, another time he was eſteemed as one that deceived the People: if at one time he be acknowledged to have done many wonderful and powerful Miracles, he is again traduced that he caſt out Devils through <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the Prince of Devils: if by ſome he be ſtiled <hi>the Son of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> he is by others called <hi>the Carpenters Son, the Son of Joſeph and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> whoſe Brethren were with them: if at one time he is thought to be a great Prophet, or the Meſſiah, he is again another time called <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus of Galilee:</hi> if the People one while (by an over-ruling hand of God) entitle him <hi>King of the Jews</hi> that was to come to the <hi>Daughter of Sion,</hi> and ſing <hi>Hallelujahs to him in the higheſt,</hi> and <hi>Hoſanna's to the Son of David;</hi> yet not long after they cried, <hi>Crucifie him, crucifie him;</hi> and fulfilled thoſe horrid evils that brought their Judgements (declared by him before) upon them, in the moſt dreadful ruine of that People, with their City and Countrey unto this very day, and which muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue whilſt the time of the Gentiles (as our Saviour witneſſed) be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.23.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:31"/>
               <p>And after the foundation of the Kingdom of the Stone was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſaid by the God of Heaven, and after his Reſurrection all Power was given to him in Heaven and Earth, and he had given Commiſſion to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to preach the Doctrine of the Kingdom, and to others ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding under the firſt Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. Firſt, the Apoſtles went out with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any worldly power; and though they were indued with Power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om on high, when the holy Ghoſt ſate on them, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. like cloven tongues of fire on each of them; whereupon they were enabled to ſpeak with ſtrange languages, who not long before were poor ignorant unlearned Fiſhermen of low condition, yet were then ſuddenly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled both to ſpeak miracles and work miracles; and Divine Power was manifeſt to go along with their Preaching of the Goſpel, to the converſion of many thouſands at one Sermon; yet the powers of the world even then ſtood up againſt them, whilſt they that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned before ſpake miracles of ſtrange languages; and which was more miraculous, they heard them when there was ſo many (as the Text witneſſeth) of ſtrange Nations which heard them, <hi>every one ſpeak in their own language the wonderful works of God,</hi> yet even then they ſay blaſphemouſly of this wonderful work of God, <hi>[Theſe men are full of new Wine:]</hi> They hear of their miracles, but they ſeek to ſuppreſs them; <hi>for we</hi> (ſay the Rulers) <hi>prevail nothing, theſe men do many miracles:</hi> And they not only do not own their Doctrine, and not help to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote it, but lay hold upon them and impriſon them for preaching of it: and this did not only befal them amongſt the Jews at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but in all places were they were ſent, as the Story of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> and other Writers of the Primitive times manifeſt.</p>
               <p>Again; The ſucceeding Primitive Chriſtians, both Teachers and Profeſſors of the Goſpel of Chriſt, were not only not owned and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the Potentates and great men of the world: But the great Red Dragon had gotten ſuch ſtrong poſſeſſion of the higheſt ſeat of worldly Authority in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire at the height of it, having ſo mightily engaged them for all ſorts of Heatheniſh Idolatry, and to decline their imbracing of Chriſtianity after ſuch abundant conviction of the Divine Excellency of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> the Son of God, that in moſt places under that (then moſt ſoveraign earthly Authority) the Officers and Magiſtrates were engaged or encouraged to root out Chriſtianity (if it might be) out of the world; and how for the moſt part they acted to that purpoſe, was ſo evident, that (as an Ancient records) it was then obſerved that there was no day in the year whereupon five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Martyrs had not ſuffered, ſave one in the Calends of <hi>February:</hi> and what large Volumns have been written of the cruel and mercileſs
<pb facs="tcp:102104:32"/>deaths and martyrdoms of thoſe primitive Chriſtians, wherein they were forced to undergo thoſe ſtrange deviſed tortures and torments (beſides all leſſer ſufferings) may abundantly appear to thoſe that are obſervantly converſant in them; and even then, by a Divine Power going along with this perſecuted Goſpel in the Preachers and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors thereof, as with the Iſraelites under <hi>Pharoah's</hi> Taskmaſters, the more they oppreſſed them the more they multiplied; ſo thoſe ſhowe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of blood of the Saints made the Goſpel to grow more fertily: and as was obſerved by the Ancients, <hi>[Sanguis Martyrum, Semen Eccleſiae]</hi> the Blood of the Martyrs was the Seed of the Church. And this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all along the Primitive times, in the ten much noted Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, beſides leſs noted ones (which were like not to be a few) wherein, as by ſo many grievous and ſore pangs and throws of the Woman (the Church) then with child (through mercy) by the faith and prayers of God's People, till ſhe brought forth that Man-child, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, under the fixth Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. who threw down the Dragon (with his heatheniſh Idolatry) from the Throne, with his Sun, Moon and Stars about him, of his worldly powers, that had ſo long perſecuted the Saints in their ſucceſſions before: And this was done by the Divine Power of God's Spirit, converting that famous Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, encouraging him againſt the Heatheniſh Oppoſers, and proſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his proceedings to a wonderful ſubverſion of thoſe powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which, for the terribleneſs of their downfal, the Spirit of God decyphers much like a day of Judgment, in regard of the execution thereof, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. latter end: which though it was ſaid to be <hi>from the Wrath of the Lamb,</hi> yet there is no ſitting of Judgment, nor opening of Books, which will be at Antichriſt's ruine, when the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will begin; and as will be at the laſt ruine of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, Rev.</hi> 20. when the laſt accompliſhment of the Judgment follows up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it at the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Yet this ſeems to be the great undertaking of Chriſt to conquer his Enemies in the firſt Seal: whoſe <hi>right hand ſhould</hi> (then) <hi>teuch him terrible things,</hi> Pſal. 45.4, 5. <hi>whilſt</hi> (as is there expreſſed) <hi>he rides on in his Majeſty prosperouſly, becauſe of the Word of Truth, Meekneſs and Righteouſneſs,</hi> for the firſt three hundred years, till <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Reign, by whom the Empire of Heatheniſh became Chriſtian, having caſt off the Dragons Worſhip and Religion, and owned and received Chriſt's Religion.</p>
               <p>And this appears to be one eminent purpoſe of God the Father's giving of the Book to the Lamb, (that as it had been ſlain, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.6. but was alive again) to open the Seals thereof; and under the ſixth Seal
<pb facs="tcp:102104:32"/>was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>on contained, to execute this terrible Wrath upon thoſe Paganiſh Powers, which was the Stones eminent ſmiting of the feet and toes of the Imrge at that time, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34. and elſewhere to like purpoſe, as was ſhewed. And from thenceforward Chriſt the ſaid Lamb, as it had been ſlain, had further in Commiſſion, both by reaſon of the wicked Apoſtacy of Church and State in ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eding times, and to revenge the cruel bloodſhed and perſecutions of the Saints, with blaſphemies and other wickedneſſe of that <hi>Roman</hi> Empire before when Paganiſh, and after likewiſe when it would be poyſoned with Hereſie, and again apoſtatized by Popery; ſo that ſuitably thereunto he ſhould bring down again the power of Satan and wicked men in their ſeveral orders and places, as appears by the 7th Seal, opened by him <hi>Rev.</hi> 8. wherein he was accordingly to reveal and execute God's further Wrath, by his ſeven Angels with their ſeven Trumpets; in the four firſt of them blowing out chiefly that Wrath and Judgment upon the Weſtern Empire for the moſt part, to take away him that letted there the revealing of the Man of Sin in the Weſtern Empire, as 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. (that Antichriſt might appear) And the two following Wo-Trumpets to reveal and execute like Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon the Eaſtern Empire, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. which ſince hath almoſt been fulfilled upon it by the <hi>Sarazens</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> to this very day: And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards by the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet, to deſtroy on the ſudden all the wicked powers of Men and Devils from off the face of the Earth, at the Son of Man's coming in the clouds, and receiving his viſible Kingdom on Earth from his Father, over all Nations, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Languages, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. <hi>And the Kingdom, and the Dominion and greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Heavens,</hi> v. 27. And then at once breaking in pieces the Iron and the Clay, and therewith the Silver and the Gold, and Braſs, and making the whole Image of the four Monarchies, that is, the broken parts of the three former, with all that remained of the laſt <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, <hi>viz.</hi> the laſt and loweſt parts thereof, the feet and toes, partly of Iron and partly of Clay, to become as the chaff of the Summer-threſhing-floor, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. when the wind of that laſt wrath from that third Wo-Trumpet of the 7th Ange will carry them all away, as was ſhewed before from <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. and as may be obſerved from thoſe parallel places, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. toward the end; <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. to the end; <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. which agree with the Son of man's coming in the clouds, and when <hi>Michael</hi> ſhall ſtand up for <hi>Daniels</hi> People, and when Antichriſt ſhall have fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed his time times and a half, to ſcatter the power of the holy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then all theſe things ſhall be finiſhed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. though it is
<pb facs="tcp:102104:33"/>made evident to <hi>Daniel</hi> that his People ſhould have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> troubles before all would be finiſhed, at the laſt ſaid ſudden and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ruine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy by the deſtruction of Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>And here again, obſerve how God all along the Beaſts forty two months, gave his Spiritual Power unto his two Witneſſes propheſying in ſackcloth, thoſe <hi>Sons of Oyl,</hi> (as they are called, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.) to propheſy againſt Antichriſt, to conſume him <hi>with the Spirit of Chriſt's mouth,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bring on the ſaid Deſtruction gradually, accompliſhed by the ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Angels with their ſeven laſt Plagues poured out upon him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15 &amp; 16 chapters, till that Deſtruction be accompliſh'd at the ſeventh Trumpet and laſt Vial of the ſeventh Angel, poured-out upon him about the ſaid time fore-ſpoken of when Chriſt comes in the clouds of Heaven, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. to receive his Monarchy upon Earth, ſpoken of likewiſe <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. when the Jews ſhall generally be brought home unto him, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. and when the iniquity of that Land ſhall be removed in one day, <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.9. And then will the four living Wights, with the twenty four Elders, have that honour given to them, which they were aſſured of to their ſo great exultation aforehand,
<note place="margin">See <hi>Iren. pag.</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. and whereupon all Angels and all Creatures render to Chriſt the glory due to him, which they acknowledge there to be his deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly, ſaying, <hi>Thou art worthy to receive Riches, and Power, and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Strength, and Glory, and Bleſſing, &amp;c.</hi> And then the Kingdom of the Stone will become a Mountain filling the whole Earth; when there will be given to him, the Son of man, by his Father the Ancient of dayes, Dominion and Glory and a Kingdom, that all People and Nations and Languages ſhall ſerve him, and that for ever; whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion is an <hi>everlaſting Dominion,</hi> that ſhall not paſs away (as the four former Kingdoms did) and his Kingdom ſuch as ſhall not be deſtroyed (as the four former were, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14.) with many other Texts in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> Viſions (as we ſhewed;) which manifeſt it evidently to be to the utmoſt extent of Dominion, both of place <hi>Over the whole Earth,</hi> and <hi>under the whole Heaven,</hi> as was ſaid chap. 7.15, 27. and of continuance and duration for ever while the World remained, and for ever and ever to eternity, v. 18. when that Kingdom of the Mountain ſhall be perfected in the Kingdom of Glory in the higheſt Heavens.</p>
               <p>In that viſible Kingdom of Power, Chriſt having received that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Father, he will then give it to his Saints, who ſhall then take it, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18. and manage it for him, as ver. 27. having the <hi>Judgment</hi> (that is, the authority of judging) <hi>then given to them, to reign with Chriſt a thouſand years,</hi> Rev. 20.4. And that it is the ſame King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, given at the ſame time, as the ſeries and order of the Prophecy
<pb facs="tcp:102104:33"/>of <hi>Daniel</hi> and of the <hi>Revelation</hi> both manifeſt, and the ſame Authority of Judging in the like expreſſions of Ruling and Governing, is in both places aſſigned to the Saints, as followeth: For firſt,
<note place="margin">Judican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di poteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as illis facta.</note>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Rev. <hi>20.4.</hi>
                        </bibl> 
                        <hi>It is ſaid,</hi> I ſaw Thrones, and they ſat upon them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Dan. <hi>7.9.</hi>
                        </bibl> 
                        <hi>So</hi> I beheld till the Thrones were pitched down, and the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>that is, the Judges,</hi> were ſet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Rev. <hi>20.</hi>
                        </bibl> And Judgement was given to them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Dan. <hi>7.22.</hi>
                        </bibl> And Judgement was given to the Saints of the moſt High.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Rev. <hi>20.</hi>
                        </bibl> And the Saints lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>Dan. <hi>7.</hi>
                        </bibl> And the Saints poſſeſſed the Kingdom, with Chriſt the Son of Man, that came in the Clouds of Heaven.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But after the finiſhing of the ſaid thouſand years Reign of Chriſt with his Saints on Earth, we are to obſerve what Chriſt in <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.7, 8, 9, 10. further explains ſhall be fulfilled concerning the laſt wicked attempt of Satan after he ſhall be looſed for a little ſeaſon, verſ. 3. from his thouſand years impriſonment in the bottomleſs pit; all which time he was bound, that he could not ſeduce the Nations until the ſaid thouſand years were ended; namely, that after that time was finiſhed, that he ſhall then ſeduce the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> the wicked Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites then in the World, who ſhall then become very numerous in the four quarters of the Earth, from whence he ſhall tempt them to come with a joynt conſent; who being a wicked generation that had been forced in the thouſand years, unwillingly yet-outwardly did conform to the holy and good Government of the Saints ſucceſſively, unto whom before time they were neceſſitated to be ſubject for the ſaid thouſand years ſpace, though againſt their own heart, yet ſhall think then upon Satans ſeducement and conduct, to free themſelves from their yoke by attempting to compaſs with their multitudes the Camp of the Saints, and even attempt to beſiege the beloved City too, the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> that came down from God out of Heaven, even Heaven it ſelf upon Earth; where the bleſſed and holy raiſed Saints had all the thouſand years before happily beheld Chriſts glorious Preſence, ſhining bright with light and comfort upon them, the Lamb being in each reſpect the light of that City, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.1. expecting by ſuch means to free themſelves from that (by them ſuppoſed) heavy yoke of the Saints good Government, that ſo the Kingdoms of the World might again be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Kingdoms of Satan, and of themſelves his Vaſſals: Upon
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102104:34"/>which abominable attempt of Satan, and thoſe by him ſeduced hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, the Vengeance of God by fire (as formerly upon the Beaſt and falſe Prophet) ſhall again fall from God out of Heaven upon them and devour them, and thereupon the Devil that deceived them be caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lake of Fire and Brimſtone, where the ſaid Beaſt and falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet were caſt above a thouſand years before, to be perpetually there tormented with them: unto which will ſucceed the end of the World, and the general judgement, when again <hi>the Judge will ſit, and the Books will be opened, and another Book will be opened, which is the Book of Life; and the Dead ſhall be judged out of thoſe things that ſhall be written in the Books, according to their Works:</hi> as follows, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſucceds Eternity of Bleſſedneſs or Miſery to every Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, accordingly as they ſtand or fall in that general Judgment.</p>
               <p>And thus briefly of the main things of Chriſts Kingdom in its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſtates, of the Stone, and of the Mountain filling the whole earth, with what reſpects the beginning and ending of the latter ſtate of the Mountain, namely, that it begins upon the deſtruction of the firſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> to wit, of the Turk and Pope, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39. before the New <hi>Jeruſalem, Ezek.</hi> 40. to the end of the Book, which ſhall be called <hi>Jehova Shamma, the Lord is there:</hi> and at the end of the 1000 years reign of Chriſt and his Saints, will ſucceed the attempt and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat and ruine of the laſt <hi>Gog and Magog,</hi> of wicked hypocrites againſt the Camp of the Saints, and the beloved City, as was ſhewed; upon which will enſue the end of the World, and the general Judgement. Now in the ſecond ſtate of it, we have conſidered the Founder of this Kingdom of the Mountain, the God of Heaven; and the Donor of it, the Ancient of Days; the Receiver and Owner of it, (<hi>Luk.</hi> 19.12.) the Son of Man, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.15. alſo the time of the ſetting up the firſt ſtate of it, <hi>viz.</hi> the Kingdom of the Stone, namely, <hi>In the days of one of thoſe Kings,</hi> in the height of the Roman Monarchy, in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> days: the manner how it was ſet up in the firſt ſtate, <hi>Not by power, nor by might, but by the Spirit of the Lord of Hoſts, Zech.</hi> 4.6. Alſo the ſpiritual force and prevalency of it, to beat down, and break in pieces, and ſmite the Image in the Feet and Toes of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> likewiſe of the largeneſs of the tender of the Grace of the firſt ſtate, to every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture capable, to all ſorts of People ſucceſſively, till at the time of the end it ſhall be perfected in the Kingdom of the Mountain, filling the whole Earth; which outwardly, viſibly and gloriouſly, as well as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and ſpiritually, God, the Ancient of days, will give to his Son, the Son of Man, upon the deſtruction of the Beaſt and falſe Prophet; when Chriſt, the ſaid Son of Man, ſhall come in the Clouds of Heaven
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102104:34"/>to receive it, who ſhall retain it to the end, deputing its Rule and Judgement to his eminent raiſed Saints and Martyrs, who ſhall exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the ſame for him, over all People, Nations and Languages under the whole Heaven, for the thouſand years, which afterward Chriſt will deliver to God the Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. for ever after the Worlds end. In which Kingdom the Body of the Jewiſh converted Nation, with faithful Iſraelites, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. and the abundance of the Gentiles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in at their riſing, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall continue conjoyned in their ſucceſſions in one throughout the ſaid Period, to the end of the World.</p>
               <p>Now the moſt evident Fore-runners of this Kingdom of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, are theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, The awakening (<hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2.) of the Iſraelites and Jews from their bondage and diſperſion, to ſeek for their promiſed Land by ſuch an <hi>Elias</hi> as God will ſend to them before the great and terrible day of the Lord come, as <hi>Malachy</hi> ſpeaks, Chap. 4, 5.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The eminent fall of Antichriſt, the Pope, at the riſing and aſcending of the Witneſſes, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>The firſt is founded upon two Scriptural Computations: 1. Of the 1290 days of years, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.11. from the moſt probable <hi>Epocha</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> time, about 366. or as learned <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> 363. ending about 1656. or ſooner, which is computed, verſ. 12.45 years before the ſtanding up of <hi>Michael</hi> the Prince of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s People, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1, 12. about the year 1700. 2. Of the Turks date to ſlay the third part of men, being the ſixth Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9. for doing of which his time is ſet down by an hour, a day, a month, and a year; which date of his Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> reckons to be 396 years, which began not long after 1300. as Chronologers compute them, and to end about the ſame time: both which together may ſerve as a Key to open the myſtery of that largeſt number of 2300 years, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. fore-ſpoken of in the fifth head of the Roman Monarchy.
<note place="margin">Pag. 34</note>
               </p>
               <p>Again, 2dly. That Antichriſts eminent fall is near in the tenth part of the City, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. ſeems probable, 1. From the beginning of his riſe at one hour with the ten Kings, or his crowned Horns, that ſhould give their power to the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. which ſeems to be manifeſt about 406. by the Author of <hi>[Excidium Antichriſti]</hi> lately publiſhed, and ſo his date reacheth to about 1666.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By the pouring out of the Vials, 1. Upon the Popes Earth, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering him to be Antichriſt. 2. Upon his Seas, when many Nations, Tongues, and People fell off from him. 3. Upon his Rivers and Fountains, which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſeems firly to apply to the Popes Emiſſaries, Prieſts, Jeſuites, and other ſeducers, who were reſirained by a Law made by Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> whereby they had blood to drink, <hi>&amp;c. Rev.</hi> 16.6. with like things then done elſewhere, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſince which time in about 100 years that third Vial &amp; two others are conceived to have paſſed, and now the ſixth to be begun; ſo that (probably) about the like proportion the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Vial may be poured out to the Popes utter ruine, when the ſeventh Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet begins to ſound; (probably) about the foreſaid period.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="observations">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:102104:35"/>
               <head>Some Obſervations from the whole.</head>
               <p>IT remains now in the laſt place, that we lay down ſome general Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, to be left to be enlarged, and particularly improved by all judicious and diſcerning Chriſtians, as Gods Spirit may guide them therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> As the ſummary of all Religion ſhews that the eternal Counſel of God is always exactly &amp; perfectly in fulfilling, ſo Gods more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial revealing to the greatly beloved Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> the orders, the times, the ſtate, the nature, the riſe and the ruine of the four great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies of the World, that ſhould ſucceſſively oppreſs the <hi>Jews;</hi> to inform the faithful in all ages following, that God orders according to his moſt wiſe counſel, all the ſufferings and tryals of his People, men cannot add in the leaſt to their meaſure or continuance, above what God hath in his moſt wiſe counſel appointed. Therefore truſt in the Lord at all times and in all conditions; for as he orders all things in the greateſt Monarchies, ſo all for the good of his poor and faithful ſervants yet in wonderful varieties of his moſt wiſe diſpenſations ever to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored. Therefore, <hi>if ye ſee injuſtice or oppreſſion in a City, marvel not at it:</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As God revealed to <hi>Daniel</hi> all the <hi>Jews</hi> oppreſſors in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with the times of them, both how many, and how long they ſhould be ſo held under by them: So thereby take notice how gracious God is to his faithful People in the worſt times, to let them have ground of comfort, that his Peoples Sufferings are here limitted by himſelf, and that they might not be without ground of Faith and Hope of good in the iſſue of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> As <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw in Viſion the riſe of all, ſo the ruine of them; to teach the Faithful in their ſucceſſions to look through the dark Clouds and Storms of Perſecution, to the bright Sun-ſhine that will follow, and in the dark night of afflictions to the riſing of the Sun of Righteouſneſs with healing in his wings; and that the triumph of enemies in wickedneſs doth but foreſhew their dectruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As the <hi>Jews</hi> at the height of their provocations were ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivated by the <hi>Babylontans;</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> before them by the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrians;</hi> ſo therein the impartial juſtice of God is to be acknowledged, who is ſo far from ſparing a People, upon whom his Name is called, if they ſin againſt him, that the nearer he hath brought them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he doth the more ſeverely puniſh them when they greatly rebel againſt him.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:102104:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> As <hi>Judah</hi> had a deliverance after ſeventy years from the captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> by <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> but not the Tribes of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> from <hi>Aſſyria:</hi> So thoſe that God brings moſt near unto him, and have moſt intereſt in him, he is propenſe to ſhew them more mercy, than others that have been more eſtranged from him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> As there was a remarkable degree of mercy vouchſafed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Jews</hi> after their return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> even till Chriſt came in the fleſh; thence take notice, That Gods ancient Promiſes to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful forefathers will certainly take effect, though their Poſterity may for a long time be unworthy thereof, for the generality of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> As <hi>Judah</hi> after their reducement from captivity, were much in an oppreſſed and troubled eſtate, by the three laſt Oppreſſors of them; ſo God ſuits the condition of a ſinful People, though near unto him, anſwerable to their unworthy walking towards him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eighthly,</hi> As <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> have had ſo long time of captivity and bondage under ſo many Oppreſſors ſucceſſively: So thence may be obſerved the greatneſs of their provocation, that moved God ſo heavily, and ſo long time, by ſuch ſad calamities ſucceſſively to ſcourge them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> As God had made great and large promiſes of wonderful mercy to his People after all the times of their ſufferings were over: So he would by the Viſions of <hi>Daniel</hi> let all his faithful People know thathe was mindful to perform them all, though it was very long before their deſerved ſufferings would be accompliſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tenthly,</hi> As the wonderful excellency and grace of Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom on earth hath been anciently recorded, and excellently deſcribed by the Spirit of Chriſt in his Prophets, in all times of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſucceſſively: So the wonderful bleſſedneſs which the faithful ſhall enjoy in that ſtate, will prove worth patient waiting for, when it ſhall be enjoyed by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> As the <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians were ſurrogated in the room of the rebellious <hi>Jews,</hi> when they were caſt off; So obſerve, That long enjoyment of Gods mercie, if it be abuſed, is far from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailing it upon any People; and, that no People have been ſo eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from God (as were the <hi>Gentiles</hi> a very long time) but God may have mercy and grace in ſtore for them in his good time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> As the times of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have been eminently more gracious ſince the <hi>Jews</hi> long rejection and cutting off; So the heinous abuſe of ſuch clear and precious grace will make their judgement the more heavy, as will be manifeſt in the Popes deſtruction, eſpecially who hath moſt wickedly turned the glorious Revelation of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102104:36"/>of the Goſpel into a pernicious myſtery of iniquity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirteenthly,</hi> And as the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> after the thouſand years of Chriſts reign upon earth, will ſin moſt heinouſly againſt all former examples of judgements, and againſt the moſt glorious grace ſet before them in the Kingdom of Chriſt the ſaid thouſand years; So when they ſhall againſt all means and warnings, and from an inward hatred of goodneſs follow Satans laſt ſeducement, to attempt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, with their multitudes, the Camp of the Saints about, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved City: Then God will thereby be ſo highly provoked to wrath both againſt them and the Devil together, that his juſt vengeance will fall from heaven upon them, and utterly abandon both Satan and all wicked men from the face of the earth, ſo putting an end unto the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourteenthly,</hi> As the fierceneſs of Gods wrath declared from his Word will be ſhortly executed upon Antichriſt and his followers in theſe laſt and worſt dayes of Satans wicked Dominion; So let the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof be a ſtrong enforcement to all ſorts of men now eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to flee far from <hi>Babylon</hi> and Popiſt ſeducements, leſt they partake of thoſe Plagues and heavy Judgements haſtening to fall on her and them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifteenthly,</hi> As God hath in his Word recorded ſeveral remarkable computations of times, reſpecting both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dayes: So both ſhould thence be awakened to behold and conſider ſuch marks and ſigns of theſe times, that they may eſpecially in theſe laſt dayes prepare for the glorious coming and appearance of Chriſt, now near approaching: For (ſaith he himſelf) of theſe very times; <hi>Behold I come as a thief, bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, leſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame,</hi> Rev. 16.15.</p>
               <p>For now the Adverſary watcheth ſo much the more diligently and maliciouſly, endeavouring to deſtroy, and that as a ramping and roaring Lyon ſeeking whom he may devour, by how much he knoweth that his time in the world is ſhort. <hi>And that day alſo will come as a ſnare upon all them that dwell upon the face of the whole earth,</hi> as our Saviour himſelf ſhewed, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.35. after he had particularly declared many ſigns of theſe laſt times, now for the moſt part accompliſhed: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in the next <hi>verſe,</hi> enforceth this duty of watching with prayer, to this end, that they might eſcape thoſe terrible things that then at Chriſts appearing ſhall come to paſs, and alſo ſtand before the Son of man; which they cannot do without keeping their garments, to wit, thoſe ſpiritual garments of Juſtification by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, and of inward Sanctification by Divine Grace in their hearts and ſouls,
<pb facs="tcp:102104:36"/>ſhewing their living in the Spirit, by their walking in the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Both which garments muſt be adorned with a Godly and Chriſtian converſation in the ſight of men, <hi>that they ſeeing their good works, may glorifie their Father which is in heaven:</hi> Otherwiſe their ſhame, as our Saviour forewarns, will be manifeſt before himſelf, the great Judge (then) and Angels and men. And they will be found naked, and lye open (then) to the fierceneſs of that great and dreadful ſtorm of the wrath of the Lamb; when will be ſuch a time of trouble, as never was ſince there was a Nation, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. And ſo great an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake as was not ſince men were upon the earth, ſo mighty an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake and ſo great, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18. So that well might our Saviour at ſuch a time pronounce them bleſſed that ſo duely watch and pray and keep their garments; which he of his infinite mercy teach and enable all his faithful People rightly to perform; who by his own moſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful grace worketh all their works for them, in the uſe of his own good means, and according to the good pleaſure of his moſt holy will, to the eternal praiſe of divine Goſpel-grace in him the Beloved. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="to_the_reader">
               <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THE Penman of the preceding parcels, aiming therein next to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Divine Grace and Truth, at this double benefit to all ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Church of God in theſe dayes, to prevent their evil, and promote their good, whether they be Independant, Prelatical, or Presbyterian, as to Diſcipline, provided they be truly Chriſtian, as to Principles of Doctrine. Yea, and yet further,
<note place="margin">Though Seas bear the <hi>names</hi> of their diſtinct Coaſts, it is all the ſame kind of Water.</note> even aiming at the true good of ſo many inviſible mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſts Church, as yet remain to be called out of great Myſtical <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> it ſelf, that they may not partake of any of her Plagues, <hi>Rev. 18.</hi> And this for all ſuch the rather, however differing in the Modes, Forms, and Wayes of ſeeking, ſerving, and worſhipping of the great God in Spirit and Truth, and ſo being real members of Chriſts myſtical Body do love him in ſincerity; and conſequently muſt love one another as ſuch (though the ſelfiſh perſons of all thoſe ſaid wayes love themſelves only in reality, and all or any others only for ſelf-reſpects) But let ſound Chriſtians of all ſorts know,
<note place="margin">Though Rivers fall fiercely into the Seas, yet ſuddainly become one with it: there is one Faith, one Hope, to Gods People: one God and Father of all: who by ſuch graces in Chriſt makes his all one in Spirit and ſoul: We muſt therefore beware of Diſunion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that herein is Satans Maſter-piece in theſe divided, and ſadly ſtill dividing times, to work what diſ-union he can amongst thoſe which he knows (though few yet believe it) ſhall ſhortly be one, or made perfect in one, as our Saviour
<pb facs="tcp:102104:37"/>prajed, <hi>John 17.</hi> Therfore to prevent Satans deſign, all ſuch have great need to pray and labour earneſtly for Unity; and this cannot be without putting on the Apoſtles bond of perfection, true Chriſtian charity, ſo excellently decy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered <hi>1 Cor. 13.4, 5, 6, 7.</hi> whoſe Office is not ſo much to find what fault ſhe can, as to hide what faults ſhe may in others; and is not ſo ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous about the cutting off or ordering the hair of Chriſts Spouſe, or paring her nails (which nature will teach) as to preſerve her body and perſon ſafe and ſound; and yet this Charity will not be without her inſeparable compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo Purity, but ſhe muſt keep cloſe to her three neceſſary attendants, Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Righteouſneſs, and Sobriety, according to Gods pure Word, <hi>Pſal. 12. and 19.</hi> for without theſe, all pretences of Purity, Piety, or any thing reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion, how ſpecious outwardly, or otherwiſe ſoever they may appear, are but meer vanity at the beſt, lut alſo leſides that, may have many abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That one Rule for edification, <hi>1 Cor. 14.26.</hi> would regulate all ſuch things amiſs: for what reſpects Order and Decency, <hi>verſ. 4.</hi> would ſo in their natural courſe fall in of themſelves.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Penman apprehending theſe Doctrines of Chriſts Kingdom, very pertinent to improve and encreaſe theſe needful Graces, gives thee, Chriſtian Reader, this direction, to uſe this his prefent help to thoſe ends. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That thou mayeſt find the Key of ſuch Doctrines by ſome light of the Book of the <hi>Revelations</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt: uſe that ſhort cornpriſal in the <hi>Fore-runner,</hi> dated <hi>May 20. 1664. pag. 22, 23, 24, &amp;c.</hi> And that <hi>Summary</hi> of the ſaid Book, given to the Lamb, <hi>Rev. 5.</hi> In the <hi>Irenicon, pag. 26, 27, 28, 29, &amp;c.</hi> which, together with the Paper of <hi>December 7. 1664.</hi> In the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner, pag. 26, 27, 28, 29, &amp;c.</hi> Which may ſerve for many perſons as an <hi>A. B. C.</hi> to ſpell the meaning, in ſome uſeful meaſure, of that divine Book; and reckon likewiſe the Abridgment on <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions, a like <hi>A. B. C.</hi> to ſpel out ſome things of that Book alſo: and by the help of both thoſe <hi>A. B. C's.</hi> thou art like to make a more profitable uſe of the enſuing <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel,</hi> which contains again, a Summary of the main matters of both thoſe Books; joyntly witneſſing unto the ſame divine Truth (though the <hi>Revelation</hi> is the ſure Key to unlock <hi>Daniel</hi>'s (before ſhut up) Viſions in great part) by which means, with Prayer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> thou mayeſt by Gods bleſſing find much light come into thy ſoul, reſpecting many other portions of holy Scriptures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſuppoſe thy reaſon wil ldirect thee to turn to pertinent quotations: <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of Scriptures, only pointed out for brevity. And <hi>Secondly,</hi> Of any other of theſe parcels referred unto for thy advantage; and theſe latter parts after the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> being attentively ſo peruſed, will much enable thee to get a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the ſubſtance of all matters contained in the whole work.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 19. line 22. read</hi> ſheltered, <hi>not</hi> ſhattered.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102104:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
